¬ Localised file for campaign descriptions 11/13/2006

{CAESER_IN_GAUL_JULII_TITLE}House of Julii
{CAESER_IN_GAUL_JULII_DESCR}The year is 58 BC.\n\n
Gaius Julius Caesar has been appointed Pro-Consul of Rome and Governor of Cisalpine Gaul. He is responsible for the protection of the 'Friends of Rome'. These are the Gallic tribes who have agreed to be clients of the Republic: they give up their independence, but receive protection and the other benefits of Roman rule.\n\n
The Germanic Helvetii tribe, however, are not friends of Rome or friends of the Gauls. They have begun to move south west into the lands occupied by the Aedui and Sequani peoples, two of the tribes who look to Rome and Caesar for protection.\n\n
This is Caesar's chance. In the chaos of a war perhaps all of Gaul could be brought under Roman control. Any general who manages this would gain enormous political prestige at home, perhaps even enough to become master of Rome.\n\n
This is your chance to match Caesar's achievements. Take the Roman Legions to victory in Gaul!

{SONS_OF_MARS_JULII_TITLE}The House Of Julii
{SONS_OF_MARS_JULII_DESCR}You are the new leader (pater familias) of a young and upcoming noble (Patrician) family.\n\n
You have been given a military command by the Senate and People of Rome (SPQR) and must help forge a safe, strong and lasting empire in Italy.\n\n
Your first objectives are to repel a barbarian attack, just near Rome, and then move to take control of the town of Tarquinii, to the north west of Rome.\n\n
As your tutor will have told you, It is up to you to "seize the day" (carpe diem).

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_JULII_TITLE}Seleukeia
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_JULII_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Very Challenging\nExperienced EB players looking for a serious challenge should consider this campaign. Seleukeia has a difficult starting position but grows more capable as the campaign proceeds.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nAlexandros knew. The key to his empire lay in Babylonia, not in Makedonia. After his death, Seleukos, another Makedonian, fought to regain Babylon for himself, and in 312 the city welcomed him with open arms and great joy. He repaid that generosity, retaking Susiana and then Media, pushing the limits of his new empire back to the Indos and then west to Syria, claiming much of Anatolia as his own. As a great old king he passed the throne to his son Antiochos seven years ago. Now the new king, of Makedonian and Persian blood, and master of an empire that stretches from the shores of the Aigaion to the borders of the Indos itself, must struggle to hold together his father's glorious gains. The wisdom of Achaemenid advisors, and now ancestors, will continue to guide this young empire and her army, but one thing must be remembered: Babylonia is still the key, even now, to the greatest empire in the world.\n\n
Alexandros' vision of a strong infantry combined with a Persian willingness to use local soldiers and their own styles of warfare have given the great king a powerful army for his empire. Persian light infantry and men from across the empire fighting in the Makedonian phalanx will be your basic foot soldiers. Greeks who have settled in Syria will form the bulwark of your regular troops and the best of their number, trained at the highest levels, are equipped for use as Argyraspidai, the famed "silver shields" and the legendary Hypaspistai. With the strong and fast Thureophoroi and their heavily armored cousins, the Thorakitai, few armies in the world can match your forces. Recruit skirmishers from across your empire and combine them with your cavalry forces, which include Median armored Lonchophoroi and Greek cavalry armored in the manner of the Kataphraktoi, to complete your mighty forces.\n\n
A great king must not allow his provinces to rebel, as petty princes are attempting to do in the "kingdoms" of Pontos, Baktria, and Armenia. Such is the burden of ruling a vast empire and you will not have the luxury of dealing with your enemies one at a time. Crucial decisions must be made in dealing with these rebellious princes; will you allow them begin their own empires, perhaps lessening your greatness, or will you risk your armies in an attempt to bring them to heel. The Ptolemaioi to the south were once allies to your father, but they now see their best hopes of expansion coming at your expense. They will send countless soldiers across the desert into the middle of your realm; if you are to preserve your Empire, they must be turned back, especially in southern Anatolia. Expand where you are able; some nearby cities are prime targets, isolated as they are from allies. Also, it would be unwise to take lightly the beating of hooves from the north. Our heavy cavalry have a difficult time standing against the great hordes of Armenian, Sarmatian, and especially Parni horsemen, and letting too many fall defending the northern borders will leave the Empire’s heartland exposed to attack from the treacherous Ptolemaioi. But take heart, great king! The blood of Alexandros and the Achaemenid rulers of the past will aid your throne, which is the greatest in the known world! Take heart, and prosper!

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SCIPII_TITLE}Hayasdan
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SCIPII_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Nigh-Impossible\nOnly those looking for the toughest challenge should consider this campaign. Hayasdan begins with an incredibly difficult starting position but grows more capable as the campaign proceeds.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nArkah, we salute you.\n\n
In the time of uncertainty ahead you will lead us, and the people look forward to your kingship! We are more or less free of Seleukid rule, but you should never count them as friends. The nobles are awaiting your visit to their estates, and many a young Hai noble son is training in the arts of hunting for when you will come. Our people are free, or freer than before. It is true we were a satrapy under Persia, but it was a good life then and we did not feel any oppression. Now again we have our own king, and perhaps a new Greater Hai will be born.\n\n
As our Arkah you will lead the host to battle or send your sons in your stead. The Nakharar and Azat nobles will provide you with the elite troops in your army, the armoured cataphracts. These men either fight solely as lancers, where their task is to punch a hole through a weak spot in the enemy formations, or as archers who pepper the enemy from afar and then close in when the battered enemy is tired or try to flee. The estates will also raise Persian cavalry armed in the Median fashion; tough cavalrymen armed with javelins and tabar axes. They will serve you well in harassing the enemy flanks and pursuing a beaten foe. The lower classes, the shinakans, will fill the ranks of your infantry; they can be relied on to do their duty, but are no match for the Hellenic phalanx infantry. Remember, Arkah, that warfare is an art. You have to know what troops to use during battle and when to use which troops. No unit is a war-winning force in itself. Cataphracts alone against phalangitai is disaster, as is infantry alone against horse archers.\n\n
Our kingdom is either on the verge to expand and grow greater, or to fail and be a footnote in history. Your rule barely encompasses all of Haikakan proper; yet with cunning and good use of our armies that can change. To our north, in the Caucasus, there are small mountain kingdoms who are allied to none, and who can be conquered early. North of the Caucasus mountains there are endless steppes with no strong rulers, but the Sauromatae are north of them and they might impose their rule further south. Should you face them, falling back to the Caucasus could be a useful to fight them on your terms and in the hills where their cavalry will not have an advantage. To our west old Persian nobles rule large estates, yet if we attack here we may come into conflict with the upstart kingdom of Pontos. They might consider us easier prey than the Seleukids, so do not leave your western border undefended. To our south are our "lords" the Seleukids. Be polite towards them as their empire is large, and so are their armies. Should they find the mountain passes between our homelands and Syria poorly defended, they might want to reduce your title to satrap by sending an army or two. Also be wary of rumours from the south. The Seleukids have many enemies; should they wage war on many fronts, you might be able to 'grab' some land from them. To our east there are more independent rulers, but across the Kaspia Thalassa the Pahlavan roam. They may not be an enemy to us now, but keep and eye on the coasts of Kaspia Thalassa to see if any Pahlavan armies approach. Know your neighbours and understand your armies, and our people will be remembered in the annals of history. 

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_CARTHAGE_TITLE}Pontos
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_CARTHAGE_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Nigh-Impossible\nOnly those looking for the toughest challenge should consider this campaign. Pontos begins with an incredibly difficult starting position but grows more capable as the campaign proceeds.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nFor hundreds of years Hellenic colonists have lived and traded in the cities on the southern coast of the Pontos Euxine, but only a few miles inland their influence stopped and their hardy mountain neighbors kept the hills and passes to themselves. Alexandros brought the Makedonian spear and horse and unified all of Anatolia, but his death and the vastness of his empire have spread his successors too thin. Their attention diverted, a new kingdom has quietly crept along the coasts and mountain edges. Mithridates, descended from a long line of Persian satraps who continued to serve Alexandros and his successors, has seized towns and allied himself with the newly arrived Galatians, and within the last decade has dared to rebel against Alexandros' successors. Though tensions have been eased, the new kingdom of Pontos, ruled by an opportunistic Persian family, in possession of several Hellenic colonies and determined to avail themselves of the benefits the Hellenes have provided them, find themselves trying to secure the mountain regions under their control and expand along the coastline. The Pontos Euxine is there for the taking and the riches that trade brings to them, along with its influence in the Aegean and Mediterranean, will be the source of their power.\n\n
Pontos sits on the edge of the wine-dark, cool waters of the Pontos Euxine. And even though you hail from the foothills of the Pontic Alps, it is the destiny of your kingdom to rule the waves. Together with Hellenic ingenuity and your own followers’ natural seamanship, your goal must be to make Pontos a mighty sea-borne power, for it is not by land that you should hope to gain your glory. No, for that, the Seleukids are too powerful, and too wary of your designs as an independent ruler. You must look north, to the waterways that will lead you to the rich granaries of the Tauric Bosporos. Only once your supremacy is established on the waves that have given name to your state, can you hope to begin expanding your influence over the more traditional Hellenistic world. For you to succeed, your enemies must be bled white before you make them bleed red.\n\n
A mixture of Hellenic, Anatolian, and old Persian units are available to the rulers of this new kingdom. But choose wisely; peoples with many different methods of war surround you. Persian spear infantry will keep the order in your cities, but it will take Hellenic hoplites to take control of their other Hellenic brothers on the coasts. The inland axemen and more types of spear and javelin will provide you with the power needed to move in from the coasts, and should you equip them properly, the Galatians can provide elite and versatile spearmen as well. Light peltasts and slingers will be recruitable, and for more money Syrian bows will aid your cause. Of course, cavalry will be a great aid in your conquests. Light javelin cavalry can be trained quickly. Heavier steppe cavalry from the north and east can also be recruited and your Persian ancestors will provide elite armored units that may ride into battle alongside exotic scythed chariots if you choose.\n\n
With Pontos, inherently, you will look to secure your power first by controlling the sea and nearby coastal regions, a number of whom are other petty kingdoms come together as allies against the Seleukids. But their individual cities are tempting targets, and they will be such to other powers as well. The Armenians are weak, but know their mountain passes well and have horse enough to thwart you. Expansion across the sea is possible, where Thraikians have territories too vast to control effectively, but can strike your trade routes and destroy your power centers there if you do not provide enough support. The Thraikians, and further away the Makedonians, are more Hellenized, but powerful foes. Yet the single largest threats to your fledgling kingdom are those whom you know best: the Seleukids. If you are not cautious, they will send armies over the mountains, take back their lost possessions, and push your armies into your beloved sea. If you handle the situation carefully, alliances through marriage and profit and against common enemies may keep them at bay long enough for you to build your strength. Yours is the newest kingdom of countless ones that have been established on the shorelines that feed into the great ocean at Herakles’ pillars. Heed the failures of those that came before you. It depends on you and no-one else, if your fledgling kingdom will wither and die like any other, or rise to the challenge and follow in the great footsteps of its ancestors.

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_EGYPT_TITLE}Qarthadastim
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_EGYPT_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Moderate\nPlayers with limited Rome: Total War experience are encouraged to try this campaign first.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nA strong commercial and agricultural activity, experienced mercenary armies and a powerful and advanced navy have been sufficient to keep our nation secure and prosperous for centuries. But now new challenges arise. An expansionist and warlike city from the italian peninsula is rising and they respect no treaties you may have made with them in the past. Their vast manpower resources and their resolute determination in expanding their empire, even if that implies capturing lands and resources from former allies by means of war, may throw our prosperous nation and colonies very shortly into a prolonged conflict.\n\n
In order to prevail if such confrontation occurs, you have to be strong and ready for total war. Access to powerful mercenary armies which your coffers can afford are still plenty. Battle-hardened, agile and extremely skilled sword infantry as well as fast and experienced light and heavy cavalry from Iberia; devastating and highly ranged slinger units from the Balearic Islands; swift and javelin-armed expert light cavalry from Numidia and fearless Celtic warriors from Southern Gaul and Northern Italy are available to complement perfectly with your highly trained african phalanxes, elite heavy cavalry and terrifying trained war elephants. To command so diversified armies, you have at your services some of the brightest and most experienced generals to have ever walked on earth. However, if you are to engage in such prolonged conflict with such a vastly outnumbering foe in terms of manpower, even your rich coffers may falter. You have to prepare your country not only to field specific elite units but also large, reliable and battleworthy standing armies if you are to prevail.\n\n
It is also advisable to strengthen and extend your peace and trade treaties throughout the Mediterranean to military ones and, most important of all, to unite your own people under your leadership, struggling together towards the ultimate cause, the prosperity of the Kart-Hadastim.
As mentioned, the Romani are our enemy or will be soon. They are at war with the Greek kingdom of Epeiros and our spies say they have the advantage. The Romani will turn their eyes to us soon, and you should prepare our army in Elymia for war. The Romani might not be as rich as us, but their soldiers are better trained and disciplined than ours. Although the Romani are not our only neighbours we should worry about. The Ptolemaioi to the east are among the few in the world who can say they are as rich as us and not be accused of lying. We trade with them, and as you know with trade comes gold and rumours. Should they hear we are in trouble they will send soldiers across the desert, but not for aid. Should they be in trouble though, we could do the same! Closer to home, we also have the Numidians to the east, a nuisance at best and a threat at worst. They have no council or tyrant to rule them, but their petty kings might attack us from time to time. Taking a more drastic measure against them might be appropriate should they pose a threat. In Iberia our colonies are bringing us much wealth, but wealth attracts warlords and troublemakers. The Iberians who live north of our colonies are disunited and under no strong ruler, but rumours are trickling in from the mountains that some of the tribes are starting to form closer bonds. Do not disregard these rumours. The Iberians might be savages, but warlike savages who often serve in our armies and serve well too. Should you invade them, remember that it is their land you fight on and they are expert ambushers. And they will unite against any invader.\n\n
Rule wisely, young general, and victory shall be undoubtedly be ours!! 

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_GAUL_TITLE}Aedui
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_GAUL_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Challenging\nExperienced RTW players will find this campaign a good introduction to EB. Aedui has a good starting position but becomes much more difficult as the campaign proceeds.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nYou have come to power by way of election, and we honor you, as the selected master of our people. You are the Vergobret, chief magistrate of the Aedui, and the leader of all fair and just tribes of Gaul. The lesser magistrates, the representative chieftains, and assemblies of the people, have declared you as our leader in this time. As such, you have been found to be the most wise, most skilled, and most forward thinking of all our aristocracy. Let us hope that is true, because we need you. We are threatened. The Arverni, with their heathenish god-king, wish to incorporate all of Gaul under his rule, and claim we are weak. The free tribes are ever looking to expand their lands, and have turned away from us after the disastrous events of war with the Arverni. The Germanic tribes are expanding rapidly and overrunning the edges of the lands, and the Romans, still angered by the sack of Rome, wish to exact revenge upon all Gauls, regardless of their loyalties. We must be prepared to fight, and we will need a cunning leader. We are the rightful heirs of the Bituriges, Gaul passed to us. The rebellious criminals of the Arverni have beset us; they plague our merchants in clear defiance of all laws. They are little more than thieves, but they are thieves with an army. The wars with them have drained us; our armies are weakened, morale is low, and more tribes abandon us or flock to the cause of the wretched Arverni. This has been our fault, in many ways, but we have chosen you, Vergobret, to remedy this.\n\n
Our immediate concern should be the nature of Gaul itself. While the Arverni are sometimes open to reason, they are power hungry. The free tribes we can buy or conquer, and incorporate them into our greater whole; with a display of strength, they should return to us without great issue or dispute. I'm sure many will prefer the path of joining us, and will see it as their greatest option, once we reassert ourselves as the masters of Gaul. However, open war with the Arverni again is inevitable, and will almost surely be devastating, even in victory. If we can postpone it and build our army, perhaps we can reconquer Gaul while at great advantage. We have a fair mix of soldiers at our option. They are brave; good infantry and quality cavalry, capable of defeating many foes when properly led. A problem of expense must be expressed, however. Gaul is rich, but we control too little for it to be of great good to us. Our client tribes in the south are endangered. Cut off from our bulwark, they cannot defend themselves long, and reinforcing them will require either long roads through rebellious or independent tribes, or trying to pass directly through Arverni territory. We should be forethinking, of course, and see beyond the immediate conflict as well. With the Arverni subdued or conquered, our most immediate concern may then turn to the Germanic tribes. They are good for trade and business, but they are viciously expansionist, and wouldn't have need of trade with us if they conquer Gaul; and they know this. If we do not conquer them outright, we should at least enforce our borders. The Belgae, the Sequanes, the Bononae; they all report the brutal raids and invasions of the Germans. Taking the Belgae and using them to strengthen our borders against invasion may be a path to explore. The eastern tribes aside, the Romans may be a threat. They may not seem a huge issue at the time, but they yet harbor resentment against Gaul. Perhaps we could take advantage of their current situation; they may have a number of potential enemies. We could ally with them long enough to destroy the Romans, but in doing so we risk strengthening a potentially unforeseen enemy. Alternatively, we could seek to ally with the Romans and use them against the Arverni, but opinions of that matter are quite split. In the north, the Britons do not seem much of a problem, but sometimes they get ambitious. The British isles are rich, and northward expansion is not ill-advised; an island fortress against the expansions of enemies will at least provide us with a final redoubt if our plans fail.\n\n
There was a time when Keltoi controlled great amounts of land. They were confederated, allies. But that fell apart, and all we are doing now is holding onto the last strains of a great history. That can be changed, though. We still have life in us, and great smiths, warriors, and a glorious culture. We deserve the glory that was robbed from us by centuries of collapse and infighting. Uniting Gaul is only the first step in forging a grand empire. Our people have a great system of leadership. We elect great leaders, we select our own kings and judges and chiefs. We allow people their own lives. Our gods demand it. And that is good. They also demand the utter destruction of our enemies. And that is also good. Those who oppose us, who try to destroy us, are evil. There can be no argument of this. We act in accordance of the divine laws of the gods. Those who act against them must be destroyed. Those who offend the gods, must be eliminated. We must crush them, and do so devoid of mercy for them. Such enemies are below swine, and should be slaughtered in the manner befitting them. And our enemies are numerous, and your warriors' thirst for the blood can be sated a thousand times over. However, their impetuousness can be a threat. While your eldest and best trained warriors are disciplined, the younger have the tendency to dash headlong into the path of the enemy, and replacing the dead can be difficult; it is expensive, and only so much of the population is available to fight. To truly forge an empire, you will have to press every advantage as far as you can. You will have little opportunity to relax until you can establish a united, strong, country with strong defenses. It seems almost impossible, but all great undertakings should be. The impossibility of this situation is what makes it glorious, and will ensure our dominance for centuries to come.

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_GERMANIA_TITLE}Sweboz
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_GERMANIA_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Challenging\nExperienced RTW players will find this campaign a good introduction to EB. The Sweboz have a very good starting position but it becomes somewhat more difficult as the campaign progresses.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nHail! ("Be with Luck granted by the gods!")\n\n
Lo! We of the Suebi, both jarls and karls have raised you upon the shield to be both the King over the chieftains of the tribes and the War-Lord of the troops in this time of greatest need. Your noble birth traces a path of lineage to the old gods, and the elders of our people expect leadership equal to your ancestors. The brave warbands shall follow you eagerly in search of glory and plunder, so long as your luck holds fast in the surge of battle, and your sword arm remains lively.\n\n
Our great tribal confederation stands tall on the brink of wealth and fame, but also danger stands against us from all sides to check our advance. Across the great river Rhine in the West, lie the rich and fertile lands of the Gauls. These people are strong warriors and well-armed, but they have grown soft with easy living and are torn by their own rivalries. And over the mountains to the south, trade brings rumors that the city-dwelling people of Roma are growing ever stronger. At some point we should consider reforming our military, expanding warbands from marauding to occupation by gathering those warriors composing others' army, levied and plentiful, so that we might make our neighbors' fertile lands our own.\n\n
But we must also keep our mind on other concerns more close at hand. Our tribes, the Semnones, the Marcomanni, the Langobards and the Hermunduri, to name only a few of our mighty confederation, are mighty amongst the peoples of the North, but our ancient rivals look upon our success with jealous eyes. The Cherusci are a proud tribe and would be happy to usurp our status, if we were to give them such an opportunity. Though short of our numbers, they have proven themselves fierce warriors in the past, and there is no reason to believe they would not relish the opportunity to demonstrate it once more. Their threat to us would be particularly heightened should they make common cause with the Chauci or the Chatti. Perhaps it would be wise for us to make the first move and bring all three of these tribes into our alliance, either by reason or the sword.\n\n
And there are other threats further afield. The peoples of Scandinavia are stirring and with the Gotones and Geats among them, they could threaten us from north and east if not prepared. And there are more rumors, men who say that a great wandering army from amongst the mysterious peoples of the Cimbri will march through our lands and bring war and fire to the far off lands beyond mountain and river. Subduing these and other dangerous warriors such as the Warini would secure us against attacks from the North and bring us farther along the coastlands where ample booty lay waiting to be plundered.\n\n
We lack not for courage, strength, nor wisdom in war, by the will of Tiw; and what we lack in arms and armor we will remedy with the riches of conquest. With the blessings of the gods, good judgment and cunning strategy, our borders might stretch to encompass the whole of our raiding territories, and become the richest lands any have ever seen. Our warriors rend themselves impervious to harm or defeat through faith and courage. Who among our enemies would stand against us when we fear not even death? Circumstance and the beckoning call for glory has played our fate into your able hands, shape it as you will.

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_MACEDON_TITLE}Makedonia
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_MACEDON_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Challenging\nExperienced RTW players will find this campaign a good introduction to EB. Makedonia has a challenging starting position but grows more capable as the game proceeds.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nMakedonia. A land of contradictions. A land of soft, rolling lowland and rough, heavily forested highland. A land famed both for its horses and its men. The land from whence Philippos and Alexandros marched and made the world tremble in awe. It is a land of endless possibilities, but that knowledge is also known outside of its boundaries.\n\n
Whatever the case be, you are the one that controls Makedonia. You control the great estates from where its famous cavalry comes, as well as the tough but unruly men from the hills that fill the ranks of its resplendent infantry. It is you that has taken control of the land which made it even possible for the Seleukidoi and Ptolemaioi to attain the position they have now. Why should they not be subservient to your majesty? The majesty of the Makedonian king? The rightful supreme ruler of the Hellenistic world as master of Alexandros’ birth ground?\n\n
All political musings aside, you are one of the great European powers, if not the greatest. From your power base in Makedonia itself, you control large tracts of the traditional Hellenistic world. Such power creates jealousy, however. As a result, your enemies are numerous. To the south, your rule in Hellas proper is contested by leagues of Hellenistic city states in the Peloponnesos as well as in Aetolia. Then there is the perpetual danger emanating from the old powers in the cities of Sparte and Athenai. All want to throw off the shackles of Makedonian rule, and to get it they want to take the rule of Korinthos and the control of the isthmus from you.\n\n
Meanwhile, your control of the Greek islands is contested by the Ptolemaioi and their hated ally, that foul city of Rhodes and its statue built of the remains of your father’s siege weapons. They want the city of Mytilene on Lesbos, which grants you control of the Thrakian Bosporos and the northern Aigaion.\n\n
To the north, there remain the perpetual threats of the Thraikians and the Illyrians, who are still more than ready to come through the mountain passes and raid your lands. To the west, there is a growing power which has already managed to take control of the Hellenistic cities of Megale Hellas. These Romaioi have even managed to defeat a descendant of Alexandros himself! Perhaps they have their hungry eyes directed to your domains as well. What to do against such numerous enemies?\n\n
While developing naval strength is a possibility, your infantry is the core of the Makedonian army. Basic hoplite soldiers from the older Hellenic cities under your control are available as are the better equipped sarissa-bearing soldiers, of varying levels of ability and training, for which Makedon is so well-known. The best Makedonian pikemen are, of course, the famous Argyraspidai, or "Silver Shields". Their armor is better and their training is more thorough and they will hold the line in tough situations. You can supplement these with the most elite soldiers, trained in your best barracks, the Hypaspistai. They have shorter spears and function like traditional hoplites except for their mobility and mail armor. They are some of the toughest and most versatile soldiers available to any army in the ancient world, but they are also some of the most costly to train and maintain. Other foot units such as the Thureophoroi are still somewhat experimental and use the almond shaped thureos shield, behind which they attack with javelins and then their short swords. The infantry is also supplemented by inexhaustible supplies of javelin-throwing Akontistai, traditional slingers, Greek archers, higher classed skirmishers known as Peltastai, and even Thrakian Peltastai, which are extremely common and very useful. Following a proud tradition, the Makedonian cavalry are not significantly changed from the days when Alexandros led their charges. Thrakian light cavalry is very effective and mobile, but the men of Thessalia are among the best that the Makedonians are able to muster, trained from birth as they are in fighting on horseback. Alexandros' Hetairoi cavalry were the elite of the Makedonian horse though, and they still are, carrying their twelve foot lances and heavy armor.\n\n
Will you be able to lead these proud soldiers to the same lengths as their ancestors that served Philippos and Alexandros? Will you be able to reestablish Makedonian hegemony over Europe and keep Ptolemaic influence out of the Aigaion? Perhaps you will even be able to avenge your father by tearing down that accursed statue of the Rhodians! There are a great many ways to go, oh king. Choose wisely. There is a fine line to walk between success and failure.\n\n\n\n
Historical Situation in 272BC\n\n
For two short years, Antigonos Gonatas had securely held the title of King of Makedonia. Well-educated, the son and grandson of some of the greatest of Makedonian kings, and newly married, Antigonos was about forty-five years of age, and seemed destined to carry on his family's legacy and the power of Makedon. But a year before, when he had been asked to send troops to Italy to help Pyrrhos and his campaigns there, he refused. Pyrrhos then came back from Italy and Sicily and gathered his troops to settle a grudge with Antigonos. Antigonos was defeated at least one time, and possible more. Pyrrhos seized Pella and the royal Makedonian tombs at Aigai. But he allowed his Gallic mercenaries to plunder some of the royal tombs and lost any popular support in the region for those reprehensible acts. Though Pyrrhos claimed the title of King of Makedon for himself, Antigonos never gave up the throne. He was forced back to the sea coasts outside of Pella and at Demetrias, but Pyrrhos did not succeed in driving him into the sea.\n\n
Now, in 272, an exiled Spartan king, Kleonymos, has asked Pyrrhos to lead an army against the Spartans, and Pyrrhos has withdrawn from Pella. Epeirote armies are still in Makedon, but with the capital of Pella, which is destined for even greater glories under the new king, and his most important city of Demetrias, Antigonos is still strong. As to the other "shackles" of Hellas, by which the Makedonians have been able to keep the mainland under their control, they remain strong. The Akrokorinthos, or the great citadel at Korinthos, is still in your hands, controlling passage to the Peloponnesos, and Chalkis gives you a base to expand to the east when the time comes. One other friend, the city of Mytilene on Lesbos, also provides you with the best naval possibilities of any faction inside the Aigaion Sea.\n\n
While developing naval strength is a possibility, your infantry is the core of the Makedonian army. Basic hoplite soldiers from the older Hellenic cities under your control are available as are the better equipped sarissa-bearing soldiers, of varying levels of ability and training, for which Makedon is so well-known. The best Makedonian pikemen are, of course, the famous Argyraspidai, or "Silver Shields". Their armor is better and their training is more thorough and they will hold the line in tough situations. You can supplement these with the most elite soldiers, trained in your best barracks, the Hypaspistai. They have shorter spears and function like traditional hoplites except for their mobility and mail armor. They are some of the toughest and most versatile soldiers available to any army in the ancient world, but they are also some of the most costly to train and maintain. Other foot units such as the Thureophoroi are still somewhat experimental and use the almond shaped thureos shield, behind which they attack with javelins and then their short swords. The infantry is also supplemented by inexhaustible supplies of javelin-throwing Akontistai, traditional slingers, Greek archers, higher classed skirmishers known as Peltastai, and even Thrakian Peltastai, which were extremely common and very useful. Following a proud tradition, the Makedonian cavalry are not significantly changed from the days when Alexandros led their charges. Thrakian light cavalry was very effective and mobile, but the men of Thessalia were among the best that the Makedonians are able to muster, trained from birth as they are in fighting on horseback. Alexandros' Hetairoi cavalry were the elite of the Makedonian horse though, and they still are, carrying their twelve foot lances and heavy armor.\n\n
What do these forces benefit a commander who chooses poorly in the diplomatic world at large? Keeping Epeiros and the grouping of Athens and Sparta preoccupied with each other would seem to be a wise path; anything that preoccupies Pyrrhos while you rebuild your infrastructure from his recent attacks would be helpful. A weakened Thraikia, after Lysamichos' death and the Gallic invasions, may be your best option for early expansion. Byzantion is a potential treasure-trove of wealth and Tylis and Sardica are both nearby and would not anger any other powers if you expanded in their direction. Thermon and the riches of Delphi are nearby as well. While Pyrrhos might be your first concern, ensuring that the men of Athenai and Sparte do not free the rest of their brothers in the Peloponnesos is also extremely important. You must hold Korinthos if you have designs on the whole of Hellas, otherwise it might be in your best interests to withdraw your forces and move to the north and possibly east. The eastern coasts of the Aigaion Sea are within easy reach, but the strongholds at Pergamon and Nikaia are not to be taken lightly. You have few friends outside of the loyal men in your army's ranks. The Ptolemaioi are now drawing closer even, as they intrigue with Pyrrhos and the Athenians as well. The Seleukeis might be powerful allies, albeit hesitant allies currently, but have no real love for you or your house. But in a situation where there are few friends, it will be in your best interest to maintain and even develop that relationship while wars wage elsewhere. Also in the east, keeping an eye on Pontos and their fast ships will also be of the utmost importance if you expand to the northeast and into Anatolia. The Italians are of little concern to you now, but could become allies if Pyrrhos poses enough of a problem to them as well. There is no easy path for Makedon, and it would take but a few slips to be pushed into the sea entirely and allow a pretender to claim the glories of Philippos and Alexandros and the title of King of Makedonia. But an able leader and keen eye to take advantage of the political situation might be able to win many victories on the field and bring a second great age to Aigai and Pella once again!

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_PONTUS_TITLE}Saka Rauka
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_PONTUS_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Nigh-Impossible\nOnly those looking for the toughest challenge should consider this campaign.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nFor generations, ever since the time we reigned supreme in these lands, we rarely made contact with our old homeland. However, the strength of our neighbors to the east is immense and though we have not warred with them for several generations, their power threatens us; by these I especially mean the Togar nomads, who are more popularly known among their settled neighbors to their southeast as the Ngiwat-tieg. They own many grazing lands and even some of the oases southeast of the Heavenly Mountains; they seem to have the ability to subdue even the peoples of the great distant plains east of the Mountains of Gold, who are quite different in both language and appearance to many of our tribesmen, though they are still nomads like us. It seems that we may have to, perhaps one day, abandon these lands to wherever we can make a new home for ourselves. Though the power of the Togar is threatening, we do not fear them; we will fight to the death, no matter where we may end. Yes, I remember, from the stories that my forefathers use to tell us, that it was a long time ago when our people migrated from our old homeland. We were originally powerful neighbors northwest of those settled people who call themselves the descendants of Xwaehaex, whose warriors are skilled in the use of military arms and neither lack valour nor courage; over 300 years ago, their duke, Mjuwk of Dzin, defeated our ancestors and allies in battle and took our grazing grounds, yet our people took the long and difficult journey to the rich grasslands north of the Heavenly Mountains, braving desert and snow, for we refuse to bow down to Mjuwk of Dzin even though at the time his power extended to all four corners of the earth.\n\n
But decadence had taken over the Tsyuw rulers of the Xwaehaex people and they are now divided, though recently we hear from our traders that the Dzin state looks like it will conquer all the others. Yet we are too far removed in space from them now to concern ourselves with their state of affairs, for Dzin's strength at the moment does not appear to directly threaten our lands. Even the powerful Togar seem to be more concerned elsewhere than on invading our lands, since our traders tell us that they are busy fighting fierce battles with the nomads to the southeast of the Mountains of Gold. But, I say, we must not be too rash in our decisions, for courage alone is not enough to defeat the powerful Togar, who are currently riding on a wave of victory against their foes and can call upon thousands of warriors from all over their empire in no time; we should look elsewhere to gain advantages rather than the east. For the time being, there seems to be sufficient wealth present to our south, in the lands beyond the Heavenly Mountains where many thriving oases exist along the edge of the Desert of Death. There are many merchants travelling between the oases, usually laden either with gold to exchange for silk or laden with silk successfully obtained from the nearest Xwaehaex state, that of the Dzin; we have need only to increase the number of raids into the region, since our raiders can only penetrate the routes between the oases along the Desert of Death, an impassable region where neither man nor army has ever successfully travelled through. To our north and west as well as the lands to the far northeast, those beyond the Togar, live nomads who speak languages, though different from ours, we can mutually understand; some of them are our allies, and we maintain trade relations with them, especially our kinsmen who rule over the Mountains of Gold; from them too, we can obtain silk, but we also maintain trade relations with the Dzin, indeed, our traders acquired the art of casting bronze and iron from the Dzin. To our southwest there are Haoma-drinking nomads who live in a plain southwest of the Heavenly Mountains where the Haoma plant grows in abundance; our traders say that they were once very powerful but were later subjected by the Chorsari, who in turn were later themselves subjected by a king the Yavanas call Megas Alexandros. These Haoma-drinking nomads we also trade with as well as the Mazsakata, those nomads whom the Yavanas call the Massagetai, and it is from them that we learn of the Yavanas and the Chorsari peoples and of their crafts. The Yavanas, who call themselves Hellenes, are still lords of the former territories of the Chorsari, including the land they call Baktriane and other territories west of the Silis river. Our neighbors of the southwestern plains who have fought many wars with them and who constantly raid their borders tell us that they are not entirely easy to defeat, but we have yet to meet them in battle and test our strength against theirs.\n\n
The world is vast and many peoples lay beyond the edge of the endless steppes, and though we are surrounded by a variety of peoples, some powerful and some not, we do not fear any of them - if there were no powerful peoples around for us to defeat, how can we ever obtain glory and riches? Is it not honorable for a warrior to die young in battle after achieving many victories so that he cannot grow old and be despised as a coward by his fellow tribesmen? Before Mjuwk of Dzin did his work, we were almost lords of the entire Tsyuw realm, raiding the Central Plains until the Tsyuw lord moved his capital eastwards and a duke of Dzin finally defeated our forces. During that time, we were the equal of the Togar who were our allies, and both the Togar and the Tsyuw respected and feared our power. Today, we neither lack valour nor skill, yet only a great rauka can lead us to victory against the most powerful of foes. And so if it is our good fortune to have such a rauka within our ranks, it does not matter which direction we advance toward, it will not be too long before we become lords of all and outdo even the achievements of the ancients.

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SELEUCID_TITLE}Romani
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SELEUCID_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Moderate\nPlayers with limited Rome: Total War experience are encouraged to try this campaign first.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nWe have never yet feared anything that was human. But the divine, Fortuna herself, we always hold a dread of her as faithless and inconstant; and, for the very reason that in war she has been as a favorable gale in all our affairs to this point, and we still expect some change and reflux of things. We never act without first taking the auspices, in public and private matters, and with crimsoned hands and smoke from the altars in our eyes we give the utmost importance to the omens our augurs take from them, just as Romulus himself did, on the first day of our city’s existence. Even after successful auspices and a victorious campaign, secure and free from the danger of a now defeated enemy, we dread the change of the goddess at sea or entering a narrow mountain pass, whilst conveying home our victorious army, vast spoils, and a captive king. Nay, indeed, after we return, and see the city full of joy, congratulating, and sacrifices, yet still we distrust, well knowing that Fortuna never conferred any great benefits that were unmixed and unattended with probabilities of reverse. Therefore it is not in the auspices alone that we place all of our trust, but we also put our faith into the customs of our fathers, and into the steel we fashion into the bane of our enemies. The chief glory and mainstay of our Res Publica, preserved intact and safe up to the present time with salutary steadfastness, is the tenacious bond of military discipline, and it is the gods themselves who have vouched that military discipline jealously conserved will win over the leadership of the whole of Italia, rule over many cities, great kings, mighty nations, the jaws of the Euxine, the shattered barriers of the Alpes and Tauri, all from our origin in Romulus’ little cottage. Our scars have scarcely healed from our last campaign, and they will never disappear, but we remain victorious and unconquered, as yet small, but trusting in the gods and in Fortuna as well as we might. The Conscript Fathers and our Res Publica, the Senatus Populusque Romanus and our gods, our brothers and fathers, we all carry down the mos maiorium for our sons and descendants and even for the great city itself. We trust in our past and with Fortuna’s good blessings and courage and arms, and a devotion to the gods, we trust in our glorious future as well.\n\n
Our soldiers are drawn from the various classes of our society. Some of the general multitude serve as skirmishers in the ranks of the Acensii, Rorarii and Leves; After that is the heart of the Roman army, our heavy infantry. The Hastatii, the Principes and the Triarii are the backbone of any force we bring to the field of battle. Our cavalry, few in number but brave, are composed of the richest class, the Equites. This force is bolstered by many of our new allies, such as the Samnitii and the other tribes who have wisely succumbed to our protection. It is the sacred responsibility of all those under the rule of the Res Publica in time of war to rise up to defend Roma and her allies, and this they do with vigor. While they are not as fearsome or bred exclusively for war as the Gallus, or as professional as the mercenary employed by the Graeci or the Carthaginienses, each one knows what fate should befall their families and the Roman populace were they to suffer defeat in battle. Our advantage over the enemy lies not only in the determination of our citizens, but on the superior flexibility in battle of our legions. No foreigner shall ever enter as a conqueror into Rome, as long as her citizens draw breath!\n\n
As powerful as our armies have thus far proven themselves to be, the Senate is constantly aware of the numerous threats that conspire to overwhelm our strengths and we advise you to take heed of our advice on these issues in particular. Our expansion in Italia has provided us with some measure of protection to the northeast, but barbarian tribes to the north constantly harry our cities and conquered territories in the north of the peninsula. The Aedui and Arverni both covet the best farmland south of the Alpes, and it is from their grasp that the Padus Valley must be taken if we hope to secure the peninsula entire. They are pressed by the Germani tribes farther to the north and by peoples to their west and northwest as well, and it would be wise for us to gain further information on their domains and activities for the time being. We are thankful that the Samnites are at long last defeated and the Lucani and Bruttii will not last long alone. You understand that our hands are now full with the conquest of the remainder of Italia, but we must not allow the Celtae peoples to advance unchecked any further south of their present territories. The two most dire threats to the well being of the Res Publica exist in the person of Pyrrhus and the people of Carthago. The Epeirote is a dangerous threat to us, even withdrawn as he is to Graecia. We destroyed much of his army, at great cost to ourselves, at Beneventum, and he may yet remove his men from Tarentum soon, but we cannot allow him to expand his base on the coast there. It would be wise to push his son and troops out of the peninsula altogether if we are able. We may even consider accepting the offer from the Carthaginians to join them in an attempt to destroy Pyrrhus entirely, but such an enterprise might only prove beneficial to them in the long run. It would be best to strengthen our numbers and men in Italia itself, rather than partake in some foolish campaigns overseas. The eyes of Carthago look upon the full of Sicilia now that Pyrrhus is removed, and our interests would best be served ensuring that the mainland sees no Carthaginian intervention or expansion. If the gods so desire it, we will face them at sea one day, but for now it seems best to increase our power here. Finally, our agreements with certain cities have benefited us in trade, but if we wish to protect them and ultimately our own interests, we must have men enough to send to their aid, and risk the full anger of the Galli, Iberes, Carthaginians, or even the other Graeci. Make no treaties with foreign peoples unless the most dire consequences threaten and do not trust the Graeci in any fashion, even those Macedones in Aegyptus who sent an ambassador to us less than a year ago. Trust in the ways of your father and his ancestors, and our gods, and you will be successful if they so will it.

{CAESER_IN_GAUL_TITLE}Caesar in Gaul
{SONS_OF_MARS_TITLE}Sons of Mars
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_TITLE}EB Main Campaign

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_BRUTII_TITLE}Baktria
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_BRUTII_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Challenging\nExperienced RTW players will find this campaign a good introduction to EB. Baktria has a difficult starting position but grows much more capable as the game proceeds.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nToday you are a satrap, but tomorrow a king. While we still bow our necks to the son of Seleukos Nikator who resides in far away Seleukeia, we will not do so for long. The Seleukid Empire is beset on its western border by the Ptolemaioi and it's attention is there. The eastern provinces of the vast empire is neglected and the barbarian horsemen from the north are attacking it's eastern satrapies and killing lawful Greeks and natives alike. Are we just going to sit idly by, while the lands that Alexandros and our grandfathers conquered decades ago are overrun by the foul Dahae or other barbarians? No. If the King of 'Arche' Seleukeia is going to let his eastern lands be overrun we will not answer to him no more. And if you break free and defend the eastern Greeks from the northern savages, the coins minted with your head on, might have the word 'Soter' or Saviour written on them.\n\n
The forces of the kingdom of Baktria are an exciting mixture of Hellenic and Iranian (and if you choose to expand there, Indian), and you will not lead them to glory on the field of battle without utilizing the best of both worlds. Mainland Hellenes straight from Thessaly and Athens served with Hellenized Iranians and locals throughout Baktria's realms. Hellenistic phalangites and Iranian spearmen will make up the core of your infantry. From the lightest armed local levies in Hellenic and indigenous panoplies to the successor state phalangites, you will have many different types of infantry from which to choose. Any Baktrian king will strive to quickly recruit a royal foot unit suitable for this kingdom and will find that the mobile and elite Baktrian hypaspists, whose equipment and style is a curious mix of a Hellenic unit adapting to the terrain, climate, and fighting styles of Transoxiana, will turn the tide of many battles. You will have to rely heavily on your countless varieties of cavalry, including regional javelin and bow mounted units of varying abilities, Median and Baktrian medium cavalry, as well as Hellenistic and uniquely Baktrian cataphract cavalry. The cavalry are supplemented by Indian elephants, which Baktria supplied in large numbers to the Seleukid empire before its independence. A variety of skirmishers are also available, including well armored and elite units as well as the Baktrian Doryphoroi, whose spears and bows make them one of the most intriguing units available anywhere.\n\n
Baktria is constantly harassed by nomads from the north, and the Seleukids will not let Baktria go without a fight. The relationship with Pahlava is stormy and you will need to choose your path with them carefully; good relations can help to stave off the decaying Seleucid influence in the region, but even then they are a threat that Baktria will have to deal with if they are to move west. The Hindu Kush provide a monumental barrier to the southeast, but any enterprising king must lead his forces across the top of the world to make India his own, and the Bactrians are better poised to do this than any other faction. With India at your back and the barbaric nomads to the north contained, the dream of Alexandros' Brotherhood of Man can become a reality that sweeps across the eastern world! 

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_PARTHIA_TITLE}Pahlava
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_PARTHIA_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Very Challenging\nExperienced EB players looking for a serious challenge should consider this campaign.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nWe are nomads, yet not for long.\n\n
We live below the Amu-Darya River and around the grasslands of the Karakum, yet not for long.\n\n
Our neighbours are few, but not to be trusted. To the north and west, the Sauromatae wander, kin to the Skythians. Their eyes are turned to their south and west, but they might find lands to conquer in the east too. Many times have we contested with them for grazing rights and they have not forgotten our sending them flying back across the Amu-Darya. To the south and east, the Seleukid Empire stretches along our border. Our young warriors have made many forays into the lands of the southerners, returning with much loot. Even our brothers, the Dahae wait for us to show weakness, ever ready to pounce. We will lead them to victory, but trust them? Never!\n\n
If you are to take on the Seleukid Empire, and one day you will have to, you must attack when the time is right. If the Seleukids have no enemies, except you, they will send their great phalanx- armies to our lands.\n
If they are at war on multiple fronts however, they might not have enough soldiers to spare, so we can grab more land from them. And the Seleukid Empire is wide and the eyes of its rulers can only see so far. Their subjects do not hold fast to their vows of loyalty and this will be our chance. Revolts will flare up in its distant satrapies, some which conveniently lie near us and could be exploited to our advantage.
And rumours from the East have reached our ears, whispers that might benefit us. The Greek satrap of Baktria lusts for a kingship of his own. And he has soldiers enough to break away from Seleukeia. Should these two ‘Successors’ fight each other we can profit. Their armies will be depleted and some of their provinces will have fewer defenders.\n\n
As a leader of the Pahlava, you will command different troops. The clans provide skilled mounted archers, and infantry levy, while the nobility among our people will provide you with heavily armoured cataphracts, trained to charge the enemy knee-to-knee. In battle, your horse archers will pepper the enemy with arrows, probing for any weak spots in their battle line for your cataphracts to charge through.\n\n
Our future is to the south, in the rich lands of Persia. Decades ago Iskander came from the west, defeating the massed host of Persia in two big battles and putting an end to the once mighty Persian Empire. The people to the south, might not look at us with favorable eyes, indeed their former kings called us Dahae, or robbers, but we share more with them, than the Greeks do. If the Seleukid Empire collapses, they might be 'persuaded' to accept a Pahlavan king who brings order, and restores the temples of their fathers, and brings honour to the teachings of the good prophet Zarathustra. Indeed, worship of Ahura-Mazda might benefit a Pahlav King, or perhaps...a Pahlav Shahanshah? Without armies, the Persians won't object.\n\n
Maybe you can be a new Kurush, a ‘Pahlavan’ Iskander. Follow in the footsteps of the conquerors. The lands to the south and east are there for the taking, you just have to know when and where to strike, if you wish to keep any spoils of war.

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_GREEK_CITIES_TITLE}Hellenes
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_GREEK_CITIES_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Challenging\nExperienced RTW players will find this campaign a good introduction to EB. The Hellenes have a challenging starting position but grow more capable as the game proceeds.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nThe two urns on the floor of Zeus' palace do indeed hold a mixture of good and evil for all. The glorious summer of the fifth century, when the relatively small poleis of Athenai and Sparte turned away the combined might of a terrible empire, when each in turn possessed naval empires and controlled lands far from their native soils, is gone. Today they are but splendid memories perpetuated by the philosophers who walk the streets of Athena’s city on the hill. The gifts of Zeus have been full of sorrow for them from the day in 338 that a teen-aged boy named Alexandros led a successful cavalry charge into their midst at Chaironeia (and even then the Athenians were tricked into believing victory was theirs; "On to Makedonia!" was their cry before the young prince stormed the gap their rash charge had left open and smashed the ranks of their allies from behind). But the god turns his sorrow now towards the north and the Makedonian fetters have been partially broken at last! Athenai herself is freed, though Attike itself cannot rest from the threat of Antigonos’ soldiers. Sparte renews the agoge military training of its sons and has men strong enough to campaign as mercenaries far from their home in the Eurotas valley. Rhodos, who has rarely if ever looked outside the shores of her island except where money could be made, possesses naval might and trading clout that might be harnessed more efficiently in tandem with other powers. Realizing it is in her best interests at the time being to do so, Rhodos has joined the other two ancient cities in the hopes of warding off their common enemies. Individually, they are small, regional powers. But sharing common interests and facing their enemies together, there is hope at least.\n\n
To cope with Makedonian advances in phalanx warfare, changes in traditional hoplite equipment have been made. Lighter armed but faster hoplitai now can chase down and deal more effectively with the threat of peltastai, and the more elite hoplitai have a better chance, with some help, of staving off the Makedonian troops. Spartan hoplitai are still among the most feared troops in the Mediterranean, but they are not easy to come by. Something of a return to ancient styles has been brought to some cities, still retained by others, where shorter spears and javelins can deal better with the threat of Roman troops than hoplites, though their use still has not been perfected against those western forces. With the help of light armed peltastai and archers, and a few cavalry options that have evolved with the rise of Makedonian equipment and techniques, there is much hope in the renewed strength of Hellas.\n\n
This alliance of city-states is nowhere near as powerful as they once were individually. Each can contribute their share and while a second great age is a distant possibility, their enemies surround them and there is no foreign shore upon which they can rely for help. Makedonia is your first concern, and you might feel their grip tighten before this very year is up; to allay fears at Pella or to smash the other fetters at Korinthos, Demetrias, and Chalkis will be one of the first decisions you must make. The best hope for Hellas probably lies in controlling the wine-dark seas that surround them, and the small rebel factions across it and on islands nearby. Krete will surely join your cause if “coerced” and indeed Sparta’s king is there even at this moment, ostensibly attempting to hire other Cretans as mercenaries. His presence might be turned to your advantage if he is supplemented with other soldiers or he recruits mercenaries there effectively enough. Though it lies but a short distance from Rhodos itself, Halikarnassos is a tempting target for many Asian powers, and the Ptolemaioi have had some troops and diplomats in parts of Karia for some time now. Other Hellenic cities across the Mediterranean may appear to be tempting, but although Kyrene and Massalia and Emporion and Chersonesos and Sinope all seem to be sources of wealth and potential allies, you will face resistance wherever you go (unless money is no object of course!).\n\n
To the chief problem at hand: the Makedonians and their king, Antigonos Gonatas, have enemies, and if at all possible it would be best to exploit their weaknesses as quickly as possible. Pyrrhos and the Epeirotes are no friend, and swift rumor from the north brings word that the deposed Spartan king Kleomenos has convinced Pyrrhos to lead an attack on Sparte before the year is out as well. However, they are at war with Makedon currently and Antigonos is a bigger threat to them; such an attack would be foolish, and Pyrrhos could quite possibly loose his own kingdom in the process. If the situation is handled tactfully by you, it might be possible to convince the Epeirotes to join your war against Makedonia and attack her on multiple fronts. You both share a common ally, in the Ptolemaioi, though you should be wary, as their helpful advisors and deep purses ultimately serve only to better themselves. As for other enemies, none are immediate. The grasping hands of power-hungry Roman generals have eyes on our western coasts, but have their hands full with Pyrrhos for the time being. The Ptolemaioi have some sympathy for your cause and their advisors and deep purses might be available, though they will ultimately only try to better their own expanding power base in the Aigaion by helping you. Beware the marauding general Pyrrhos. Although he is very talented, and he might be bought off to aid your cause, his huge forces would be expensive to maintain and he may well be regarded by both you and the Makedonians as a “rebel”, who will harm anyone that finds themselves close enough to him to be attacked. Whether or not you choose to free your kinsmen in Megale Hellas ("Italia," Hah!) and Sikelia, will be your choice, but remember and do not take lightly the sea power of the men of Karchedon. Zeus and the fates may yet return a share of good to Athena’s two favorite cities and to the shores of Rhodos. The war with Antigonos and his men will not soon abate, and this time, if indeed we are favored by the god, we will find truth in our cry of “On to Makedonia!”

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_BRITANNIA_TITLE}Casse
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_BRITANNIA_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Very Challenging\nExperienced EB players looking for a serious challenge should consider this campaign. Casse has a very difficult starting position but grows much more capable as the game proceeds.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nOn the end of the world, there is a great people. Far removed from the wars of the Mediterranean sea, the steppes, and far off deserts, they wage their own war. Your people are among the most fearsome in all of the known world, and you know this. They came to these islands, and crushed, displaced, or flatly annihilated the old people; broke them utterly. They are poets, and traders, and miners, but most of all, they are warriors. The people of the islands cry to you. They want a leader. They want some one to direct them, to lead them to great things. They want you, and who are you to deny them? This land is your right, it is the right of anyone strong enough to take it. Would you let the petty lesser tribes put you down before your chance for greatness?\n\n
The British tribes have always fought as skirmishers and ambushers, with only the rare field engagement. While this is fine for petty tribal conflicts, a potential emperor of the Britons cannot focus on this forever. He must be decisive and swift, and build a real army, not an amalgam of petty warbands. But you are the ruler of the Casse, and they have long been the most militaristic fore-thinking of the Britons. They are descended from Gauls, and employers of Gallic tactics; with planning, Britain will easily be attained, barring any unforeseen circumstances. Britain is rich; rich with tin, and silver, and copper, and livestock of all kind. A large, well funded army is quite possible, with all of the island under your yoke. The southern tribes provide the strongest, heaviest soldiers. They are the best trained, the best equipped, and the best disciplined tribes. The midlanders are more wild, lightly armored at best, but available in great number, and are relatively inexpensive, making them a good asset for overcoming an enemy by number. In the far north lay the remaining peoples. Caledonians are without remote concept of civilization. Abhorrent even to the other Britons, they are maniacs in many ways, and completely disorganized. However, they are brave. If nothing else, Caledonians are an effective shock force, and fairly disturbing to an enemy. You must rely on infantry and foot soldiers. Your cavalry is scarce and weak, and chariots are expensive. You must organize units of champions, brave warriors, who will encourage your other men to continue to fight. Britons are brave, but sometimes practicality of a situation overcomes them. Seeing great warriors of their people continue to fight will spur them on though, but champions expect compensation.\n\n
To become high king and forge a real empire, uniting Britain will be the foremost part of your early reign. The Britons are pleased to serve a powerful king, so you must show military strength. However, they also expect acumen in business matters; Britain has always been made rich by trade with distant foreign powers, and they have come to enjoy their lifestyle. You are not ready for wars with any major powers. Not yet, anyway. It may be humbling, but you are, after all, only a very small kingdom. Conquest of all of the British Isles will provide you with an easily defended enclave, which will produce great amounts of money, with proper trade agreements, and a large population from which to pool a great army of conquest. Invading mainland Europe will not be easy, but if one takes advantage of the constant wars there; attacking weakened enemies in Gaul or Germania, you can secure an easily reinforced stronghold on the mainland, and expand from there. However, this assumes everything goes to plan, and no one turns a covetous eye on your wealth. Germans are strong, brave, and numerous, and Gauls have great soldiers and relentless leaders. Further off are the ambitious Romans, Carthaginians, and the hearty Hellenic peoples, who already know the value of the island from centuries of trade. The task is daunting, to say the least, but you are not a leader of common men. You are king of the most fierce warriors, wisest clerics, and greatest champions on the whole of the planet. You are the rightful king of all of Britain, and your people deserve an empire. Their lives have been endless strife and toil at war. They deserve an empire to reflect the greatness of their achievements. As your glorious ancestors drove the wretched men who once inhabited the island from it, as they had destroyed them, so must you destroy your enemies. You must be vicious, you must be relentless, and utterly break every enemy to your will. Your people deserve peace, and peace will only be had when your enemies submit to your rule. Again, king of the Casse, I ask you, who are you to deny them? 

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_THRACE_TITLE}Epeiros
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_THRACE_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Challenging\nExperienced RTW players will find this campaign a good introduction to EB. Epeiros has a challenging starting position but grows more capable as the game proceeds.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nEpeiros, "the Mainland", the home of "wintry Dodone", the famed Molossian hounds, and of course, Pyrrhos. The regional tribes were formed into a strong state in the fourth century, led by their Molossian king. Conquests in Italy and an alliance with Rome were of little help when their great king Alexandros was killed in 330. Now another king has unified Epeiros and had great successes pacifying the Illyrians, and in battle in Italy and Sicily. Pyrrhos held much of Southern Italy and then took control of the island of Sicily except for two strongholds at the north and west. But he abandoned his hopes of conquering the island, his mother's homeland, and after a defeat at the hands of a Roman consular army he has taken his main force back to Hellas and pushed the Macedonians all the way to the coasts of the Aegean.\n\n
Pyrrhos' military forces are modeled on the Successor armies of Makedon. Heavy phalanx infantry are the core with a strong reliance upon mercenary troops which include Gallic warbands, Kretan archers, Italiote hoplites, Tarentine cavalry, and many others. Heavy Successor cavalry units as well light javelin cavalry are available, and of course, heavily armored Indian elephants, one of the most recognizable features of the army of Pyrrhos, are at your disposal, as are mechanai of Hellenic siege craft.\n\n
While your army is strong, and your position is sound, one misstep could bring your empire crashing to the ground. The kingdom of Epeiros is at a crossroads. Do you double your efforts and attempt to push the Makedonians into the Aegean from their coastal possessions at Pella and Demetrias? You are already at war and have claimed the title of "King of Makedonia" and need only drive them from the north. Their possessions in southern Hellas are more problematic though. The memory of Sicily is but a fleeting dream, and it will take much effort if you are to resume your great plan to seize the entire island. Your control in southern Italy even is in danger of succumbing to the further aggression of Rome, with whom you are at war, unless you act strategically to solidify your position or give up your last stronghold there. The Illyrian tribes to your north are strong and wild, but more effort in bringing them under your control could do much to strengthen your kingdom for further campaigns elsewhere and their help has brought great benefits to you in the past. Finally you have just been invited by a deposed king of Sparta to help him take control of the Peloponnese, though you are not openly hostile towards them. Seizing Thermon to the south and the wealth and prestige the Oracle of Apollo at Delphi grants should be an early goal, but do you dare to lead your army past the Makedonians in Korinthos and take on Makedon and the Spartans there as well? The choice is yours. But a word to the wise: "Stay away from Argos!"

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_NUMIDIA_TITLE}Ptolemaioi
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_NUMIDIA_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Challenging\nExperienced RTW players will find this campaign a good introduction to EB. Ptolemaioi has a challenging starting position but grows more capable as the game proceeds.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nMighty Pharaoh, son of Ptolemaios who was the most trusted friend and general of Megas Alexandros. Your father seized for himself the mightiest lands of his general's empire, and wrought it into a mighty empire of his own - bequeathing it you. By the might of his sword and his keen mind, your word is law along the length of the Nile, and the Western lands of the Phoenicians and Judeans, and among Northern islanders. Your rule is over the most prosperous land of Africa, and is the new home of a great rising of Greek though, centered around Alexandria. But it is also a time of war; with the treacherous Seleucids, and the reckless Diadochi of Megas Alexandros.\n\n
Your command is over one of the finest heavy phalanxes in the world, manned by a loyal corps of Greeks and Macedonians, attracted by your benevolent law. These men are supplemented by levies of the resettled Galatians and the conquered Judeans, forming their own light phalanx and auxiliaries. Though all of your land respect and admire your rule, those of the Nile are still as of yet wary of the approaching Graeco armies and are still unreliable as anything but skirmishers. You can also hire Ethiopians from the lands south of Nubia as shock infantry, assured of their loyalty, as they share no culture with the Nubians and native Egyptians. But do not ignore the sea; Egyptians, Phoenicians and Kypriotai have since the time of Odysseus navigated with ease. To control the waves of the eastern Mediterraneum Mare, is to control the whole coast.\n\n
Our position is strong and enviable. The mighty Nile is our source of income, and must be protected accordingly. We have neighbours on all sides, but none of them trustworthy. To the South are the unruly Nubians, laden with the treasure of their gold mines; and the Karthadasti to the East, rich from their stock in the world's trade. To the North are the Antigonid Makedonians, who threaten to sweep across the independent Hellenes, to fragment your power among them. Finally to the West, is the great Seleucid behemoth, ever ready to amass and traverse the Sinai to our heartland.\n\n
The Seleukids claim that they are the true heirs to Alexandros, but their falsehoods are clear, as are those of their rivals. The flood of the Nile shall send our armies forth, to crush the false heirs of Zeus-Ammon's son.

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_DACIA_TITLE}Getai
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_DACIA_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Challenging\nExperienced RTW players will find this campaign a good introduction to EB. The Getai have a good starting position but become more difficult as the campaign proceeds.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nSarmis Vasil, we are your people. Yet we are divided.\n\n
The Marisus flows through our country into the Great Donaris, the river of the Argonauts. The language of the Daci is the same as that of the Getai. Among the Hellenes however, we are better known because the migrations we make are continuous, and because we are intermingled with the Thraikes and Mysoi (Mysians). And also the tribe of the Triballoi, likewise our brothers, have admitted migrations into this country, because the neighbouring peoples force them to emigrate into the country of those who are weaker; that is, the Skythai, Bastarnai and Sauromatai on the far side of the river often raid our settlements. They will be tamed--by the wolf we swear. The king of Epeiros plots from the Haimos to humiliate our ancestors. He is dangerous from the length of his sarissa spears. The gorges shall not fall and nor shall we. Skythia borders our land as far as the source of the river Ister and the expanse of the Morsian Swamp. Their lands stretch as far as the eye can see. Their warriors fight valiantly on horseback, fleeing like the wind when threatened. They should be struck with Gebeleizis's thunder while they fight their cousins, the Sauromatai. Where the sun sets lie the Boioi and Tauriskoi. Should these new tribes look for war and raid our sanctuaries they will die from the scythed blades of Heros. We and our wild Skythian kin allowed the Hellenes to build towns like Olbia and Chersonesos so we could profit from their trade. They know to fear us, even as they call us "barbaroi". We can learn from these arrogant "polis dwellers" but can they learn from us?\n\n
Their world ends at the mouth of the Donaris and from there, their end will come, shall their strategos defy us. We are immortal, as Zalmoxis promised. He is our prophet and your master. Should your komatai fall ill the ktistai will heal them for you. Should you lack wealth, the mountains will flow with gold from our mines. They are the key to your independence. Protect them as the "civilized men" try to steal them.\n\n
Fight them in the Desert of the Getai. There Dareios the son of Hystaspes was crushed by a handful of Thraikes and Skythai. He turned back. Later on, Lysimachos, a Thraikian lapdog of Megas Alexandros, in his expedition against our late King Dromichaites, was captured alive; but he again came off safely, because he found the "barbaroi" kind-hearted. Now Makedonia uses our brothers for their armies. As I said before, Herodotos was right. Triballoi from the south and Tylis are pathetic raiders and opportunistic dogs. We harvest our wheat; they steal it from wealthier lands. We protect our children; they sell them as slaves. We're free in our lands; they're puppets to the successor of Alexandros. Their tarabostes foolishly fight each other rather than uniting for all komatai. Kogaionon, our holiest of sanctuaries has received so many messengers that the godly gates are sealed. We must be worthy of our gods before we ask for their help. Choosing a new high priest and impaling some rebels should please them. Be that as it may, our people once attained very great power, so that we could actually send forth an expedition of two hundred thousand men. Now we find ourselves reduced to as few as forty thousand, spread through twenty or so tribes.\n\n
To rule as Pavel-ter you must unite the tribes of the Karpathoi. Treat your pilleati as equals or they'll stab you with the cold knife of traitors. Give them false dreams of glory and plunder so you may gain them as subjects. Should you manage to unite all davas under your dracones, the world will tremble under your might. You may need to burn the hellene wines. They flow with poison for the manliest virtues.\n\n
We are one people. We are divided. 

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SCYTHIA_TITLE}Arverni
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SCYTHIA_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Challenging\nExperienced RTW players will find this campaign a good introduction to EB. Arverni has a good starting position but becomes much more difficult as the campaign proceeds.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nVerrix, great king, god-king, and rightful master of all the world, your people salute you. You are Arvernos in the flesh. The elections organized by the under-kings and popular assembly of warriors, and the tribal elections, have revealed the true Verrix. The Aedui assemble against us in rebellion. The Germanic tribes impose their will on what are rightfully our lands. We are the rightful rulers of the Gauls. No other concern should plague us, but their utter annihilation, and the subsequent protection of your properties against the incursions of the Germanic tribesmen. As your advisor, I will help you how I can. Do not be afraid; you are a god made flesh. Every ally is a puppet; a means to an end. Only you can bring true peace, justice, and proper rule to Gaul. Nothing else matters but this, except, possibly, the great wealth we will receive. The Aedui are too weak, and they have no manner of control. They have little way to defend this land, and the tribes will see that our strength is a boon; what good are the Aedui if they cannot defend these people? When the Aedui are broken, Gaul will be ours.\n\n
The Aedui are the true threat, however, and they still have fight in them. Their armies are essentially identical to ours. We have no great advantage to press, and they have no great disadvantage for us to manipulate. We need land, we need obedient tribes, and we need allies. We will set them all upon the Aedui and destroy them, and Gaul will belong to its rightful rulers. Subsequent conquest of the Belgae, and maybe Britain can be followed upon, or conquering the Romans, or the eastern lands. We have brave warriors, in vast number, with good weapons, good shields, and good leaders. The Aedui are likewise, and are quite vicious. Their defeat will not come easily. We will need to conquer the free tribes for greater numbers, and perhaps the Noricenes; we'll use their great and unique warriors to give us an advantage over the enemy. After they are subverted, we can go anywhere. Few around Gaul would provide more than a slight problem to our path. Many are ambitious, but their own problems will consume their soldiers; of course, the Aedui will consume ours as well. That is why allies are important. They weaken the foe, we levy the final blow. When our allies are sufficiently weakened, we incorporate them as well among the allies under the direct control of the assembly, and, thereby, under your control by proxy. The southern peninsula produces brave soldiers, and is fertile. Such an acquisition would benefit us. Some Gauls have successfully carved out kingdoms in the east; we can follow their path, or perhaps attempt to their original goal, and conquer Greece. If any problems present themselves before we can all of Gaul though, we may have to seek temporary peace with them. Irregardless, expansion into the rest of the world is clearly possible. The way has been paved and proven. With a larger concerted effort, the conquest of the east can be quite total. There is another road; into Iberia. The conflict with the Iberian tribes, if we control Gaul, will be hard still, but possible. They are tenacious and unwilling to relent, but not invincible. I would more fear the Carthaginian allies and associates with whom they deal. They control substantial territories, and aide they'd send would be quite threatening. A direct conflict with Carthage can be won, but they are rich, and can finance a large army. Cutting off their fleets will be hard, they are powerful in their navy. We would need the Veneti, and it is doubtful we could muster enough to successfully blockade them. A direct invasion of Carthage would be costly, but almost necessary, unless their relations with the Iberians collapse, to successfully conquer the Iberians. The Romans are ambitious, and harbor resentment for us, but they do not appear, at the time, to be a great threat, but waiting for them to become one is probably ill-advised. The Belgae and Bononae report the incursions of the Germanic tribes, and they set themselves against us. They want Gaul for themselves. We can perhaps turn them against the Aedui, and bide our time.\n\n
Gaul has only one rightful ruler. There is only one Verrix. You, and the subsequent Verrix, need an empire, and it will only be had at the end of a sword. You were elected, because you are divine. The selection of the Verrix is never a mistake. You are most capable to lead us; the most brave, most cunning, most fierce, and most sound leader among us. There can be no other true leader of the Gauls, and you are the proper master of the entire world. The end result of all of our conquest should be the goal of a great empire, exemplifying our culture, and the divine rule of the laws. Our destiny hangs by a thread. You are the Verrix, but you are not invincible. Do not act rashly, and try to conduct your wars without over-confidence. Even a seemingly beaten enemy sometimes has a final option. Don't give in to pessimism though. The situation is quite bright, and victory is wholly possible. You are the high king, and rightful master of Gaul. Every conquest begins with the simplest actions. Everything seems so simple when it's planned, but you are here to put plan to action, and take what is rightfully ours. We will take it all, and the wealth of Gaul will belong to us. 

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SPAIN_TITLE}Lusotannan
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SPAIN_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Very Challenging\nExperienced EB players looking for a serious challenge should consider this campaign. The Lusotannan have a difficult starting position but grow more capable as the game proceeds.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nWe have always been here. We are farmers, we are shepherds. We are warriors!\n\n
Some things never change. No matter who comes, if he tries to take our land they will learn to respect us. Many peoples and nations live south of the high mountain barrier, in the land of the acorn, of the rabbits, of the deep rivers and the gentle sun of the West. Foreigners have come and gone from across the barrier, from the merchant sea where the tuna fish abound and the never-ending ocean of the lands of tin, where high waves threaten the bravest. Anyone who comes to enslave and rule us is bound to know our determination to lead ourselves.\n\n
There is a place in the east where people learned to melt the copper without help, and a place in the west where a silver king ruled for centuries under the dictates of the verses of a poem-law. Their lust for luxury and profit made them all marry the uses and daughters of the cultivated foreigners that came from the east. Some say they have reached freedom, others that they are free no more. But, who cares? Here in the inner lands we are a thousand tribes, each earning its place in the world. To the north and south lay the brood of warriors that came across the mountains from the north, in those times when memory was dark and strange. Before them it was a time when all the country between the two great rivers was ours; it was a time of prosperity. Our herds were fat, our crops abundant, our children strong and our ancestors were honoured. But those days are gone. From the north they came, tall and fierce with broad shields and weapons of iron, to take our sheep, our grain, our blood and our sacred places. To the mountains we looked for protection, waiting for the time when we would be strong once again. And that time may well have come.\n\n
Hard times they may be, but also full of hope and potential. The world we know is becoming smaller and smaller, and we may find that there is no where else to go. Soon, the greedy foreigners of the eastern sea will not find satisfaction with their rich settlements of the coast, and come after our ancestral land. The northerners are bound to come again. Who do they think we are? We are not their slaves. It's us who decide when to fight, it's us who cultivate the wheat and eat it, and it’s for us that our sharp swords are forged. The time has come for you to lead your people, and here we must stand, or fall. Will you lead them to their place in history, or abandon them to fade into legend?

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_ARMENIA_TITLE}Sauromatae
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_ARMENIA_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Very Challenging\nExperienced EB players looking for a serious challenge should consider this campaign.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nWhy should there be an end to the fighting?\n\n
It is true that, after generations of struggle, our horses now graze on most of the lands the Scythians once called their own and that we rule over a large territory. We now count the time it takes to travel across it in months and our people and herds prosper, but the great steppe still extends beyond our dominions. There are yet more pastures to win for our flocks to grow even larger, and there live peoples not unlike us, who build no cities and dwell in wagons and tents. They also wage war as we do, largely on horseback with most as swift mounted archers that no foot troops will ever catch and some also wearing armor and wielding spears. Those will not be easy battles, but a strong ruler could bind those peoples to him and command an immense host of riders: an army such as has never been seen before.\n\n
Yes, merchants must now travel through our lands to carry their wares from east to west and from north to south and from such trading we have grown wealthier than our fathers. However, the traders still finish their journeys in the cities of the Yavanas, the Greeks, on the seashore at our southern border. All trade eventually goes there and their dwellers are rich beyond measure from it. They drink wine every day if they so wish and own all sorts of luxuries: fine pottery and bright arms and armors. What warriors would not follow a lord with such wealth at his command? How great would be the fame of such a leader?\n\n
East or west, north or south? In the end, will it matter where we ride first? Wherever we go, there will still be other lands, other nations beyond: the land of Hayasdan and the kingdoms of the Yavanas and then others whose names we do not yet know. Regions said to be even richer, fertile and of mild climate, abundant in streams and grazing. There is no man in our tribes who is not eager to please the God of War, whose name is not to be spoken aloud and whom we see in the naked sword, by winning fame and fortune through war and battle. Why, then, not let the dragon standards fly forever? Why not ride until the seas deny us passage? As long as there are riches and glory to be won and land upon which horses can gallop, why should there be an end to the fighting?

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SABA_TITLE}Sab'yn
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SABA_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Challenging\nExperienced RTW players will find this campaign a good introduction to EB. The Sab'yn have a good starting position but becomes much more difficult as the campaign proceeds.\n\nREMEMBER TO START THE EB CAMPAIGN SCRIPT (listen to the advisor)!\n\nThe waters of Almagah give us life. They come each year in great storms and turn our land into a vast garden. Fertile floodplains stretch out before our great city like an intricately woven green carpet and our might stretches out across the wadi because of Almagah’s blessings upon us. For centuries our ancestors have spread our tongue, our knowledge, our gods across the high plateaus of South Arabia with control of the trade routes of the caravans, but the gods took away our power and our sovereigns have been weak. Now our Malek, our king, a descendant of our greatest Malek, Karib Il Watar, will lead us out of Maryab and we will reclaim again those cities that once were ours. Our caravans will spread across all of Arabia and we will bring the worship of our gods to peoples who have only heard our name in whispers.

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SLAVES_TITLE}Eleutheroi
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SLAVES_DESCR}None