¬ Lines that begin with the ¬ character are comments
¬ and should not be translated
¬ Items with curly brackets are tags and should not be translated
¬ The text following tags either on the same line, or the next line
¬ should be translated
¬---------------------


¬***********************************************************
¬*                                                         *
¬* EB CAMPAIGN ADVICE                                      *
¬*                                                         *
¬***********************************************************


¬-------------------

{EBBS_Text_01_Title}	Welcome to Europa Barbarorum - Background script activation

{EBBS_Text_01_Text1}
Press the Show Me How button to activate the background script. When you reload a game always ensure you click on a settlement or the faction button before ending the turn - this will make me reappear so you can press the Show Me How button again to reactivate the background script.

{Near_Chersonesos_Text_01_Title}Be warned my king!
{Near_Chersonesos_Text_01_Text1}
These Hellenes in Taurike not only have ties of blood, but even stronger ties with those of their kind in Hellas itself: money and grain! If we encroach upon their interests here, we must be aware that they will declare war upon us. It may not matter, given their distance and preoccupation with other peoples. Should we give a second thought to our relations with them?

¬-------------------
{Attacks_Chersonesos_Text_01_Title}The day brings bad news!

{Attacks_Chersonesos_Text_01_Text1}
Seamerchants from our friends on the northern Euxine coasts have brought back word that Chersonesos is attacked. Milesians and other Hellenes founded these cities and they have been absolutely vital to our grain shipments over the past two hundred years. We must not allow this to stand. Therefore, we must now consider ourselves to be at war with the aggressors; let us hope that the Chersonesos may hold them off for the time being.

¬-------------------

{Near_Chersonsesos_Thraikia_Text_01_Title}Warning!

{Near_Chersonsesos_Thraikia_Text_01_Text1}
Byzantion and various other towns in Bithynia across the straits are allied with the king of Pontos. If we attack them, we will certainly find ourselves at war with these Pontic upstarts. This may not present much of a danger to us now, but do we risk it?

¬-------------------
{Attacks_Chersonsesos_Thraikia_Text_01_Title}Byzantion is attacked!

{Attacks_Chersonsesos_Thraikia_Text_01_Text1}
We have allied ourselves to the cities of Byzantion and provided aid to them in the past, but now they are viciously attacked. While we have our own designs on them, we must not allow the cities along the southern coast of Chersonesos Thraikia to fall into enemy hands. At the least we must now declare a state of war between ourselves and the aggressors!

¬-------------------




{Greeks_Near_Halikarnassos_Text_01_Title}Caution!

{Greeks_Near_Halikarnassos_Text_01_Text1}
For some time now the agents and even soldiers of the Ptolemaioi have been active on the coasts of Karia. Any action against the Karians or Halikarnassos will be interpreted as an act of open war against the Aigyptian kingdom, and may harm us more than we have considered. They have been our allies against the Makedonians, and are especially helpful to Rhodos, but our interests clearly conflict in regards to Karia. What path should we take? Let the citizens and strategos decide!

¬-------------------
{Greeks_Attacks_Halikarnassos_Text_01_Title}Halikarnassos is attacked!

{Greeks_Attacks_Halikarnassos_Text_01_Text1}
Our numerous interests and soldiers along the coastline of Karia are in danger. Halikarnassos and its men are attacked by the men of Rhodos and their friends on the mainland of Hellas. We have considered them our friends in the past, so we now are in a difficult situation. They know our connections and interests in Halikarnassos, yet they still attacked. Unfortunately we now must consider ourselves in a state of war against the Hellenes. Whether we attack them or try to calm the situation may yet be determined, but it is war for the time being!

¬-------------------
{Near_Halikarnassos_Text_01_Title}Caution!

{Near_Halikarnassos_Text_01_Text1}
For some time now the agents and even soldiers of the Ptolemaioi have been active on the coasts of Karia. Any action against the Karians or Halikarnassos will be interpreted as an act of open war against the Aigyptian kingdom. Do you wish to follow this course of action, given that war will probably be declared?

¬-------------------
{Attacks_Halikarnassos_Text_01_Title}Karia is attacked!

{Attacks_Halikarnassos_Text_01_Text1}
Our numerous interests and soldiers along the coastline of Karia are in danger. We must consider ourselves at war with the aggressors whether we will it or not!

¬-------------------



{Near_Kallatis_Text_01_Title}Be warned!

{Near_Kallatis_Text_01_Text1}
Any action against the city of Kallatis and its Hellenes, or against the Getai who also dwell around the city and in the countryside there will almost certainly result in a declaration of war with the Getai when they hear word of it.

¬-------------------
{Attacks_Kallatis_Text_01_Title}Kallatis is attacked!

{Attacks_Kallatis_Text_01_Text1}
The coastal city of Kallatis and the regions inland from are suffering at the hands of foreign aggressors. Our people live among the Hellenes of Kallatis, and we have long traded peacefully with them. We too have plans on bringing the city more under our control, but we must not allow outsiders to do so. We are now at war with those who would choose to attack our friends

¬-------------------


{Near_Nikaia_Text_01_Title}Warning!

{Near_Nikaia_Text_01_Text1}
 Byzantion, Herakleia, Nikaia, and various other towns in Bithynia and across the straits are allied with the king of Pontos. If we attack them, we will certainly find ourselves at war with these Pontic upstarts. This may not present much of a danger to us now, but do we risk it?

¬-------------------
{Attacks_Nikaia_Text_01_Title}Bithynia is attacked!

{Attacks_Nikaia_Text_01_Text1}
We have allied ourselves to the cities of Bithynia and provided aid to them in the past, but now they are viciously attacked. While we have our own designs on them, we must not allow the cities of Nikaia and Herakleia to fall into enemy hands. At the least we must now declare a state of war between ourselves and the aggressors!


¬-------------------



{Near_Pantikapaion_Text_01_Title}Be warned!

{Near_Pantikapaion_Text_01_Text1}
These Hellenes and their former allies in the Kimerios Bosporos not only have ties of blood, but even stronger ties with those of their kind in Hellas itself: money and grain! If we encroach upon their interests here, we must be aware that they will declare war upon us. It may not matter, given their distance and preoccupation with other peoples. Should we give a second thought to our relations with them?

¬-------------------
{Attacks_Pantikapaion_Text_01_Title}The recent ships bring bad news!

{Attacks_Pantikapaion_Text_01_Text1}
Merchants from our friends on the northern Euxine coasts have brought back word that Pantikapaion is attacked. We have long had ties with the Hellenes who founded these cities and even with their descendants who some consider less Hellenic than barbarian. But it is our grain shipments that are now at risk, and we must not allow this to stand. We must now consider ourselves to be at war with the attackers, and if possible we will send men or money at the least to help them fight off the outsiders.

¬;--------------------------------NOWE---------------------------------------------

{Pontic_Near_Sinope_Text_01_Title}My king!

{Pontic_Near_Sinope_Text_01_Text1}
Before attacking the men of Sinope, you must be warned that she is a Hellenic colony, and has close ties to Athenai and especially Rhodos. They have recently sent money and weapons to Sinope, to help steady their defenses, and if we attack them, the Koinon Hellenon will likely declare war upon us also. The city may be our best chance for expansion now, so I do not counsel you to hold your hand for good, but you must first consider these outcomes.

¬-------------------
{Pontic_Attacks_Sinope_Text_01_Title}The men of Sinope are attacked!

{Pontic_Attacks_Sinope_Text_01_Text1}
Long have we supported our fellow Hellenes in the great coastal city of Sinope. As you well know, the stout men of Miletos first populated it and brought the benefits of Hellas to the country there. She is the most powerful city on the Euxine Sea and our city of Rhodos has already dispatched money, bowstrings, supplies, and even four large catapults to Sinope to help fend off Pontos, but it may be too late. We all know that long has the king of Pontos had his eye on Sinope. A diplomat may help the situation, and find out the true state of affairs there, but for the time being we must declare ourselves at war with Pontos!

¬-------------------
{Macedon_Near_Thermon_Text_01_Title}Stay your sword, my king!

{Macedon_Near_Thermon_Text_01_Text1}
Before you send troops against the men of Aitolia, understand that the Koinon Hellenon and her soldiers will not stand for this. If we attack, we may find ourselves at war with the other Hellenes, as they consider any aggressive action upon the men who hold the holy shrine of Delphian Apollo. Given our relations with the southern Hellenes, this may be acceptable, but be forewarned!

¬-------------------
{Macedon_Attacks_Thermon_Text_01_Title}Calamity and War!

{Macedon_Attacks_Thermon_Text_01_Text1}
The Sanctuary of Apollo at Delphi is attacked by the barbarian Makedonians! We must not allow this to stand. Phillip meddled in the affairs of the Amphictyonic Council too in his day, but even he never went so far as to seize the holy shrine by force, to defile the most holy site known to us Hellenes, to pillage the offerings in the Temple of Apollo itself! By the gods! We must take to the field and ensure that it remains in the hands of the free Hellenes!

¬-------------------
{Epeiros_Near_Thermon_Text_01_Title}Hold your sword, my king!

{Epeiros_Near_Thermon_Text_01_Text1}
Before you send troops against the men of Aitolia, understand that the Koinon Hellenon and her soldiers will not stand for this. If we attack, we may find ourselves at war with the other Hellenes, as they consider any aggressive action upon the men who hold the holy shrine of Delphian Apollo. If we need their help in other areas, it would be wise to not pursue this course of action, but if you have considered this, then move forward with the attack!

¬-------------------
{Epeiros_Attacks_Thermon_Text_01_Title}Calamity and War!

{Epeiros_Attacks_Thermon_Text_01_Text1}
The Sanctuary of Apollo at Delphi is attacked by the barbarian Epeirotes! We must not allow this to stand. We have long suspected the line of the Aiakides to have their sights set on the holy mountain slopes of Parnassos, and we have long feared the day when they might decide to turn their covetous eye on Phoebos' home. That day has finally happened and the Epeirotes are taking the holy shrine by force even now, defiling the most holy site known to us Hellenes, to pillage the offerings in the Temple of Apollo itself! By the gods! We must take it back and place it in the hands of the free Hellenes once again!

¬-------------------
{Romans_Near_Thermon_Text_01_Title}Stay your sword, Imperator!

{Romans_Near_Thermon_Text_01_Text1}
Before you send troops against the men of Aitolia, understand that the Graeci and their soldiers will not stand for this. If we attack, we may find ourselves at war with the other Graeci, as they consider any aggressive action upon the men who hold the holy shrine of Delphian Apollo. Given our current presence in Aitolia and our plans for the region, this may be acceptable, but be forewarned!

¬-------------------
{Romans_Attacks_Thermon_Text_01_Title}Calamity and War!

{Romans_Attacks_Thermon_Text_01_Text1}
The Sanctuary of Apollo at Delphi is attacked by the barbarian Romaioi! We must not allow this to stand. We have long suspected the foreign interlopers to have their sights set on the holy mountain slopes of Parnassos, and we have long feared the day when they might decide to turn their covetous eye on Phoebos' home. That day has finally happened and the Romaioi are taking the holy shrine by force even now, defiling the most holy site known to us Hellenes, to pillage the offerings in the Temple of Apollo itself! By the gods! We must take it back and place it in the hands of the Hellenes once again!

¬-------------------

{Pontic_Near_Trapezous_Text_01_Title}Be warned my king!

{Pontic_Near_Trapezous_Text_01_Text1}
The men of Trapezous are allies by blood and by association with the cities of Athenai and Rhodos, and they will be furious with any attempt to harm the Hellenes there. If we pursue this course of action we risk a state of war being declared between ourselves and the Koinon Hellenon.

¬-------------------
{Pontic_Attacks_Trapezous_Text_01_Title}Trapezous is attacked!

{Pontic_Attacks_Trapezous_Text_01_Text1}
Our fellow Hellenes in Trapezous, and along the coasts in Pontos Paralios, have been attacked by barbarous king of Pontos. Trapezous, whose mother city was Sinope, has much eastern influence, but its citizens are Hellenes and it has long held out against the barbaroi inland, across the steep mountain ranges to the south. Word of this incident has reached us by the swift merchants that frequent our harbors, but can we act to stop this outrage? At the least, we must now consider ourselves at war with the king of Pontos. Let us see if the men of Trapezous are able to drive the evil doers away or if they fall to their advancing armies' might.

¬-------------------
{Armenia_Near_Trapezous_Text_01_Title}Be warned my king!

{Armenia_Near_Trapezous_Text_01_Text1}
The men of Trapezous are allies by blood and by association with the cities of Athenai and Rhodos, and they will be furious with any attempt to harm the Hellenes there. If we pursue this course of action we risk a state of war being declared between ourselves and the Koinon Hellenon.

¬-------------------
{Armenia_Attacks_Trapezous_Text_01_Title}Trapezous is attacked!

{Armenia_Attacks_Trapezous_Text_01_Text1}
Our fellow Hellenes in Trapezous, and along the coasts in Pontos Paralios, have been attacked by barbarous king of Armenia. Trapezous, whose mother city was Sinope, has much eastern influence, but its citizens are Hellenes and it has long held out against the barbaroi inland, across the steep mountain ranges to the south. Word of this incident has reached us by the swift merchants that frequent our harbors, but can we act to stop this outrage? At the least, we must now consider ourselves at war with the king of Armenia. Let us see if the men of Trapezous are able to drive the evil doers away or if they fall to their advancing armies' might.

¬-------------------

{Tsorim_Near_Ammonion_Text_01_Title}Warning!

{Tsorim_Near_Ammonion_Text_01_Text1}
Be forewarned that an attack on the holy city of Ammonion or its men will most likely be seen as an act of war against the Ptolemaioi.

¬-------------------
{Tsorim_Attacks_Ammonion_Text_01_Title}The Oracle of Zeus-Ammon is threatened!

{Tsorim_Attacks_Ammonion_Text_01_Text1}
While it is not officially a part of our kingdom, the holy oracle and city of Zeus-Ammon at the oasis of Siwa and the surrounding oases have been attacked, and our kingdom must not allow this to stand. If we ignore this the god will certainly punish us. Arm your troops and march across the desert as Megas Alexandros did, but this time ensure the barbarians will not have it and march in his great name!

¬-------------------

{Ptolemies_Near_Kyrene_Text_01_Title}Caution great Pharaoh!

{Ptolemies_Near_Kyrene_Text_01_Text1}
 Be forewarned that if we attack the Kyrenaioi, the king of Seleukeia will not stand for it. They may be powerless to stop us, but there will certainly be an active state of war if we choose to do so. Magas the traitor married into the Seleukid royal family, and long Kyrene was under his watchful eye. Consider these things before acting!

¬-------------------
{Ptolemies_Attacks_Kyrene_Text_01_Title}Our friends in Kyrene are attacked!

{Ptolemies_Attacks_Kyrene_Text_01_Text1}
Kyrene, long under the watchful eye of Magas Kyrenaios, and an ally and close friend to Seleukeia, now appears to lies under the foot of the Ptolemaioi. Word has reached us that they have seized control of the countryside nearby and are intent upon putting to death those there loyal to your kingdom. For the time being it may not be possible to retake the city, but the enmity and hatred between yours and the kingdom of the Ptolemaioi is now greatly worsened. The state of war that has existed is now increased and the treacherous thieves must be punished for this action!

¬-------------------

{Tsorim_Near_Kyrene_Text_01_Title}Warning!

{Tsorim_Near_Kyrene_Text_01_Text1}
Be forewarned that an attack on the city of Kyrene or its men will most likely be seen as an act of war against the Ptolemaioi.

¬-------------------
{Tsorim_Attacks_Kyrene_Text_01_Title}Our friends in Kyrene are attacked!

{Tsorim_Attacks_Kyrene_Text_01_Text1}
Kyrene, long under the watchful eye of Magas Kyrenaios now appears to lie under the foot of the Kathardastim. Word has reached us that they have seized control of the countryside nearby and are intent upon putting to death those there loyal to your kingdom. For the time being it may not be possible to retake the city, but the enmity and hatred between yours and the Kathardastim is now greatly worsened. The state of war that has existed is now increased and the treacherous thieves must be punished for this action!

¬-------------------
¬-------------------

{Victory_Conditions_1_Text_01_Title}Show victory conditions placeholder 1
{Victory_Conditions_1_Text_01_Text1}
To fulfill your faction's victory conditions, you must conquer these areas:\n Bartix \n\nIf you have settlements to be raided, you can review them by clicking again on the question mark.\nThis message (and the raid message) will be split into faction-specific messages as soon as FACTION COORDINATORS supply the scripting team with a small description of the factions' motives for the conquests/raids ("The Seleucids were hell-bent on restoring Alexander's empire- ...They also wanted to raid Asodat for the new sauna technology found there-")

¬-------------------

{Victory_Conditions_2_Text_01_Title}Show victory conditions placeholder 2
{Victory_Conditions_2_Text_01_Text1}
You also have to raid these:\nUranus

¬-------------------

{Iberia_vc_Text_01_Title}Lusotannan Victory Conditions
{Iberia_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must you must destroy or outlast the Romani and Qarthadastim, and conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Emain Macha, Ivernis, Burdigala, Tolosa, Tyde, Pallantia, Vellika, Emporion, Numantia, Oxtraca, Arse, Bocchoris, Sucum Murgi, Baikor, Mastia, and Gader. For your raiding targets, press the ? again.  

{Iberia_raid_Text_01_Title}Lusotannan Raiding Targets
{Iberia_raid_Text_01_Text1}You also have to raid the following: Lemonum, Avaricum, Gergovia, Massalia, Segesta, Arretium, Roma, Lixus, Siga, Ippone, Atiqa, and Kart Hadast.


{Aedui_vc_Text_01_Title}Aedui Victory Conditions
{Aedui_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must destroy or outlast the Arverni and conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Tyde, Pallantia, Numantia, Emporion, Tolosa, Burdigala, Gergovia, Lemonum, Darioritum, Cenabum, Avaricum, Bibracte, Bratosporios, Vesontio, Vindelicoppidos, Aventicos, Viennos, Massalia, Mediolanum, Patavium, Veldideno, Bagacos, Camulosadae, Ictis, Iuvavoata, Eburonum, Vindobona, and Bononia. For your raiding targets, press the ? again.

{Aedui_raid_Text_01_Title}Aedui Raiding Targets
{Aedui_raid_Text_01_Text1}You also have to raid the following: Roma

{Arverni_vc_Text_01_Title}Arverni Victory Conditions
{Arverni_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must destroy or outlast the Aedui and conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Emporion, Tolosa, Burdigala, Gergovia, Lemonum, Darioritum, Cenabum, Avaricum, Bibracte, Bratosporios, Vesontio, Vindelicoppidos, Aventicos, Viennos, Massalia, Mediolanum, Patavium, Veldideno, Bagacos, Iuvavoaeta, Vindobona, Lucarottea, Ak-Ink, Singidunum, Naissos, and Segesta. For your raiding targets, press the ? again.

{Arverni_raid_Text_01_Title}Arverni Raiding Targets
{Arverni_raid_Text_01_Text1}You also have to raid the following: Roma

{Casse_vc_Text_01_Title}Casse Victory Conditions
{Casse_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Attuaca, Emain Macha, Ivernis, Caern Brigantae, Ynys Mon, Ratae, Ictis, Camulosadae, Bratosporios, Bagacos, Darioritum, Cenabum, Lemonum, Avaricum, Bibracte, Vesontio, Burdigala, Gergovia, Viennos, Tolosa, Tyde, Pallantia, and Vellika.

{Getai_vc_Text_01_Title}Getai Victory Conditions
{Getai_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Buridava, Kallatis, Naissos, Singidunum, Sarmiszegethusa, Olbia, Gawjam Bastarnoz, Carrodunum, Lucarottea, Vindobona, Serdike, Tylis, Byzantion, Segestica, Pella, Nikaia, Eburonum, Demetrias, Epidamnos, Ambrakia, Ak-Ink, Iuvavoaeta, Chersonesos, and Pantikapaion. For your raiding targets, press the ? again.

{Getai_raid_Text_01_Title}Getai Raiding Targets
{Getai_raid_Text_01_Text1}You also have to raid the following: Athenai, Korinthos, Thermon, Sinope, Pergamon, Dalminion, Sparte, Chalkis, Patavium, Gordu Neuriji, Mediolanum, and Roma.

{Hayasdan_vc_Text_01_Title}Hayasdan Victory Conditions
{Hayasdan_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must destroy or outlast the Arche Seleukeia and conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Arbela, Kabalaka, Armavir, Ani-Kamah, Edessa, Phraaspa, Seleukeia, Babylon, Charax, Susa, Ankyra, Mtskheta, Mazaka, Halikarnassos, Tarsos, Kotais, Sardis, Ekbatana, Pergamon, Side, Sinope, Persepolis, Ipsos, Trapezous, Palmyra, Karkathiokerta, Antiocheia, Damaskos, Nikaia, Apameia, Zadrakata, Asaak, Hekatompylos, and Gabai. For your raiding targets, press the ? again.

{Hayasdan_raid_Text_01_Title}Hayasdan Raiding Targets
{Hayasdan_raid_Text_01_Text1}You also have to raid the following: Nisa, Byzantion, Chersonesos, Pantikapion, Alexandreia, Salamis, Pella, Athenai, Sparte, and Sidon.

{Pahlava_vc_Text_01_Title}Pahlava Victory Conditions
{Pahlava_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must destroy or outlast the Arche Seleukeia, the Hayasdan, and Baktria and conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Arbela, Kabalaka, Alexandropolis, Alexandreia Ariana, Armavir, Ani-Kamah, Edessa, Asaak, Phraaspa, Seleukeia, Babylon, Baktra, Chach, Charax, Apameia, Khiva, Mazaka, Karmana, Prophthasia, Susa, Alexandriea Eschate, Gabai, Ankyra, Pura, Zadrakata, Hierosolyma, Mylitene, Tarsos, Antiocheia Margiane, Ekbatana, Gava Haomavarga, Side, Kophen, Hekatompylos, Persepolis, Sidon, Ipsos, Palmyra, Marakanda, Karkathiokerta, Antiocheia, Damaskos, Nisa, Gava Mazsakata, Gerrha, Mtskheta, Taksashila, Opiana, Patala, Homna, Ubar, Petra, Bostra, Trapezous, Kotais, Sinope, Amaseia, Halikarnassos, Sardis, Pergamon, and Nikaia.

{Pontos_vc_Text_01_Title}Pontos Victory Conditions
{Pontos_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Korinthos, Arbela, Thermon, Kabalaka, Armavir, Ani-Kamah, Edessa, Phraaspa, Athenai, Nikaia, Pantikapaion, Byzantion, Sarmiszegethusa, Epidamnos, Serdike, Ambrakia, Ankyra, Buridava, Mtskheta, Segestica, Hierosolyma, Mazaka, Amaseia, Halikarnassos, Tarsos, Kotais, Sparte, Sardis, Tanais, Pella, Kallatis, Pergamon, Tylis, Side, Vindobona, Sinope, Sidon, Ipsos, Trapezous, Palmyra, Olbia, Karkathiokerta, Antiocheia, Damaskos, Chersonesos, Demetrias, Naissos, Gawjam Bastarnoz, Ak Ink, and Singidunum.

{Sauromatae_vc_Text_01_Title}Sauromatae Victory Conditions
{Sauromatae_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Gava Yazyga, Gava Roxsalanna, Gava Aursa, Upse, Tanais, Gelonus, Olbia, Chersonesos, Pantikapaion, Kallatis, Gordu Neuriji, Gawjam Bastarnoz, Lucarottea, Ascaucalis, Gava Thissakata, Ak Ink, Vindobona, Singidunum, Gava Alanna, Gava Yugra, Gava Mazsakata, Nisa, Khiva, Marakanda, Antiocheia Margiane, Gava Saka, Chighu, Gava Haomavarga, Kotais, Kabalaka, Mtskheta, Armavir, Phraaspa, Mazaka, Ankyra, Ani-Kamah, Zadrakata, Asaak, Hekatompylos, Alexandreia Ariana, Baktra, Ekbatana, Naissos, Tylis, Byzantion, Alexandreia Eschate, Chach, Sulek, and Taksashila. For your raiding targets, press the ? again.

{Sauromatae_raid_Text_01_Title}Sauromatae Raiding Targets
{Sauromatae_raid_Text_01_Text1}You also have to raid the following: Susa, Persepolis, Seleukeia, Babylon, Antiocheia, Pella, Demetrias, Segestica, Patavium, Bononia, Arctaunon, Vesontio, and Swebotraustastamnoz

{Sweboz_vc_Text_01_Title}Sweboz Victory Conditions
{Sweboz_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Swebotraustastamnoz, Gawjam Heruskoz, Gawjam Habukoz, Arctaunon, Gawjam Kimbroz, Gawjam Rugoz, Gawjam Skandzawarjoz, Gawjam Gotanoz, Eburonum, Gawjam Silengoz, Bibracte, Vindelicoppidos, Vesontio, Bagacos, Bratosporios, and Gawjam Bastarnoz. For your raiding targets, press the ? again.

{Sweboz_raid_Text_01_Title}Sweboz Raiding Targets
{Sweboz_raid_Text_01_Text1}You also have to raid the following: Aventicos, Veldideno, Iuvavoaeta, Carrodunum, Viennos, Patavium, and Ascaucalis.

{Tsorim_vc_Text_01_Title}Qarthadastim Victory Conditions
{Tsorim_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Tyde, Pallantia, Vellika, Numantia, Emporion, Oxtraca, Baikor, Arse, Gader, Mastia, Massalia, Segesta, Bononia, Arretium, Ariminum, Roma, Capua, Arpi, Taras, Rhegion, Lilibeo, Messana, Syracuse, Sidon, Bocchoris, Ippone, Alalia, Karali, Atiqa, Kart Hadast, Adrumeto, Lepki, Kyrene, and Sucum-Murgi. For your raiding targets, press the ? again.

{Tsorim_raid_Text_01_Title}Qarthadastim Raiding Targets
{Tsorim_raid_Text_01_Text1}You also have to raid the following: Kirtan, Siga, and Lixus.

{Baktria_vc_Text_01_Title}Baktria Victory Conditions
{Baktria_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must destroy or outlast the Pahlava and Saka, and conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Chighu, Sulek, Chach, Alexandriea Eschate, Gava Haomavarga, Taksashila, Marakanda, Khiva, Nisa, Antiocheia Margiane, Baktra, Kophen, Asaak, Hekatompylos, Alexandreia Ariana, Prophthasia, Alexandropolis, Opiana, Gabai, Karmana, Pura, and Patala.

{Ptolemaioi_vc_Text_01_Title}Ptolemeioi Victory Conditions
{Ptolemaioi_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must destroy or outlast Makedon and the Seleukids, and conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Pella, Demetrias, Thermon, Korinthos, Sparte, Athenai, Chalkis, Byzantion, Kydonia, Rhodos, Trapezous, Sinope, Amaseia, Nikaia, Ankyra, Pergamon, Ipsos, Mazaka, Sardis, Mytilene, Halikarnassos, Side, Tarsos, Salamis, Antiocheia, Edessa, Seleukeia, Babylon, Palmyra, Damaskos, Sidon, Bostra, Hierosolyma, Petra, Carna, Maryab, Tamane, Sabata, Ubar, Alexandreia, Paraitonion, Kyrene, Ammonion, Hibis, Memphis, Diospolis Megale, Pselkis, Meroe, Ptolemais-Theron, and Axum.

{Seleukid_vc_Text_01_Title}Seleukid Victory Conditions
{Seleukid_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must destroy or outlast Baktria, the Hayasdan, Pahlava and the Ptolemaioi, and conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Pella, Demetrias, Thermon, Korinthos, Sparte, Athenai, Chalkis, Byzantion, Kydonia, Rhodos, Trapezous, Ani-Kamah, Sinope, Amaseia, Nikaia, Ankyra, Pergamon, Ipsos, Mazaka, Sardis, Mytilene, Halikarnassos, Side, Tarsos, Salamis, Antiocheia, Karkathiokerta, Armavir, Arbela, Edessa, Seleukeia, Babylon, Palmyra, Damaskos, Sidon, Bostra, Hierosolyma, Petra, Sulek, Chach, Alexandriea Eschate, Gava Haomavarga, Taksashila, Marakanda, Khiva, Nisa, Antiocheia Margiane, Baktra, Kophen, Asaak, Hekatompylos, Alexandreia Ariana, Prophthasia, Alexandropolis, Opiana, Gabai, Karmana, Pura, Patala, Persepolis, Zadrakata, Apameia, Susa, Charax, Ekbatana, Phraaspa, Gerrha, Homna, Alexandreia, Paraitonion, Kyrene, Ammonion, Hibis, Memphis, Diospolis Megale, and Pselkis.

{Makedon_vc_Text_01_Title}Makedon Victory Conditions
{Makedon_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must destroy or outlast Epeiros and the Koinon Hellenon, and conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Roma, Capua, Arpi, Taras, Rhegion, Messana, Lilibeo, Syracuse, Epidamnos, Ambrakia, Serdike, Tylis, Kallatis, Pella, Demetrias, Thermon, Korinthos, Sparte, Athenai, Chalkis, Byzantion, Kydonia, Rhodos, Amaseia, Nikaia, Ankyra, Pergamon, Ipsos, Mazaka, Sardis, Mytilene, Halikarnassos, Side, Tarsos, Salamis, Antiocheia, Edessa, Seleukeia, Babylon, Damaskos, Sidon, Hierosolyma, and Alexandreia.

{Koinon_vc_Text_01_Title}Koinon Hellenon Victory Conditions
{Koinon_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must destroy or outlast Epeiros and Makedon, and conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Arse, Emporion, Massalia, Karali, Lilibeo, Messana, Syrakousai, Arpi, Capua, Taras, Rhegion, Ambrakia, Pella, Demetrias, Thermon, Athenai, Chalkis, Mytilene, Korinthos, Sparte, Kydonia, Rhodos, Salamis, Byzantion, Pergamon, Sardis, Halikarnassos, Kyrene, Chersonessos, Pantikapaion, Sinope, and Trapezous.

{Epeiros_vc_Text_01_Title}Epeiros Victory Conditions
{Epeiros_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Massalia, Segesta, Alalia, Karali, Bononia, Patavium, Arretium, Ariminium, Roma, Capua, Arpi, Taras, Rhegion, Messana, Lilibeo, Syracuse, Segestica, Vindobona, Singidunum, Naissos, Serdike, Epidamnos, Ambrakia, Tylis, Kallatis, Pella, Demetrias, Thermon, Korinthos, Sparte, Athenai, Chalkis, Byzantion, Kydonia, Rhodos, Trapezous, Sinope, Amaseia, Nikaia, Ankyra, Pergamon, Ipsos, Sardis, Mytilene, Halikarnassos, Side, Tarsos, Mazaka, Antiocheia, Edessa, Karkathiokerta, Arbela, Seleukeia, Babylon, Ekbatana, Susa, Charax, Persepolis, and Dalminion.

{Yuezhi_vc_Text_01_Title}Yuezhi Victory Conditions
{Yuezhi_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions your treasury must exceed 100,000 and you must conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Gava Yugra, Gava Aursa, Gava Alanna, Gava Mazskata, Gava Saka, Chighu, Sulek, Chach, Alexandriea Eschate, Gave Haomavarga, Taksashila, Marakanda, Khiva, Nisa, Antiocheia Margiane, Baktra, Kophen, Asaak, Hekatompylos, Alexandreia Ariana, Prophthasia, Alexandropolis, Opiana, Gabai, Karmana, Pura, Patala.

{Romani_vc_Text_01_Title}Romani Victory Conditions
{Romani_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must destroy or outlast the Qarthadastim, Epeiros, Pontos, the Ptolemaioi, the Koinon Hellenon, Makedon, the Aedui, the Arverni and the Lusotannan. You must also conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Oxtraca, Tyde, Baikor, Gader, Pallantia, Numantia, Mastia, Vellika, Arse, Burdigala, Lemonum, Darioritum, Cenabum, Avaricum, Gergovia, Tolosa, Emporion, Bocchoris, Ippone, Bratosporios, Bibracte, Viennos, Massalia, Bagacos, Vesontio, Aventicos, Mediolanum, Segesta, Alalia, Karali, Atiqa, Kart Hadast, Adrumeto, Veldideno, Patavium, Iuvavoaeta, Bononia, Arretium, Lepki, Ariminum, Roma, Lilibeo, Vindobona, Segestica, Arpi, Capua, Messana, Syracuse, Taras, Rhegion, Epidamnos, Ambrakia, Thermon, Korinthos, Sparte, Kyrene, Serdike, Pella, Demetrias, Athenai, Kydonia, Paraitonion, Chalkis, Pergamon, Sardis, Halikarnassos, Rhodos, Nikaia, Ipsos, Side, Salamis, Alexandreia, Memphis, Pselkis, Sinope, Amaseia, Tarsos, Antiocheia, Sidon, Hierosolyma, Dalminion, Damaskos, Sucum-Murgi, Diospolis Megale, Kirtan, Ankyra, Ammonion, Hibis, Mytilene, Naissos, Singidunum, and Kallatis. For your raiding targets, press the ? again.

{Romani_raid_Text_01_Title}Romani Raiding Targets
{Romani_raid_Text_01_Text1}You also have to raid the following: Garama, Maryab, Eburonum, Seleukeia, Babylon, Camulosadae, Phraaspa, Armavir, Meroe, Swebotraustastamnoz, and Sarmiszegethusa.

{Saka_vc_Text_01_Title}Saka Rauka Victory Conditions
{Saka_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Gava-Yugra, Gava-Aursa, Gava-Alanna, Gava-Mazsakata, Gava-Saka, Chighu, Sulek, Chach, Alexandreia-Eschate, Gava-Haomavarga, Taksashila, Marakanda, Khiva, Nisa, Antiocheia-Margiane, Baktra, Kophen, Asaak, Hekatompylos, Alexandreia-Ariana, Prophthasia, Alexandropolis, Opiana, Gabai, Karmana, Pura, and Patala. In addition you must accumulate a treasury of 500,000 mnai.

{Saba_vc_Text_01_Title}Saba Victory Conditions
{Saba_vc_Text_01_Text1}To fulfill your faction's victory conditions you must conquer these areas (highlighted on map): Maryab, Tamane, Carna, Babylon, Sabata, Ubar, Homna, Gerrha, Bostra, Petra, Hierosolyma, Alexandreia, Memphis, Diosopolis-Megale, Pselkis, Meroe, Axum, Ptolemais-Theron, Salamis, Antiocheia, Edessa, Seleukeia, Charax, Alexandropolis, Pura, Patala, and Opiana.

¬-------------------

{Epeirote_Invitation_Text_01_Title}Vergobret, the Epeirotes approach us
{Epeirote_Invitation_Text_01_Text1}
An Epeirote ambassador brings a proposal of cooperation from his king. They are in need of a strong ally to cover their backs from northern barbarians, coming across the great Danube in Illyria, and they propose that we would be these allies. We are to send an army to Illyria to capture two cities, Vindobona and Ak-Ink. The Epeirote king will send one of his armies to support our operations there. Click on me to accept the proposal or dismiss me to reject his offer.

{Epeirote_Invitation_End_Gallic_Text_01_Title}Success!
{Epeirote_Invitation_End_Gallic_Text_01_Text1}
You have successfully established a strong base in the upper Danube now and we have a strong ally in the king of the Epeirotes. Their aid on the field of battle has greatly contributed to our success. But it is your foresight and willingness to risk lives and fortunes, and even to trust the Epeirote king, that has truly allowed us to expand farther east. As the Volcae have already done, though they were searching for mercenary service, we now may expand into areas our distant kin have inhabited for many years.

¬-------------------

{Chersonesos_Event_1_Text_01_Title}Message from Chersonesos
{Chersonesos_Event_1_Text_01_Text1}
Basileus, we have received word that the city of Chersonesos, north across the Euxine, has been attacked by nomadic tribes from farther inland. Citizens who have been driven from the city have asked for our help in taking it back from the barbarians and those Hellenes who have joined them. If you send a competent general north across the sea with a strong army, more men will join you there and aid your efforts. This opportunity may provide you with a firm foothold in the region from which to expand. The loyal citizens are hiding in the forests to the north east of the city. You would be wise to contact them first before driving the barbarians out.

{Chersonesos_Event_2_Text_01_Title}Ambassador Polemon
{Chersonesos_Event_2_Text_01_Text1}
Your ambassador, Polemon, has been in contact with the exiles. They are just about to break camp and depart. Approach Polemon so he can convey your offer of aid to the exiles - they will only demand the smallest sum as sign of your good faith. Do it quickly or they will leave, or worse, in their desperation turn on us!

{Chersonesos_Event_3_Text_01_Title}Chersonesos annexed
{Chersonesos_Event_3_Text_01_Text1}
Great King, you have achieved a great victory, one that will be remembered for many generations. For years we have looked north across the great expanse of the sea. Though when a call finally came for aid we were pressed upon by our enemies in other areas, nevertheless you sent our brave soldiers north in many ships. And now we have a strong foothold from which we may expand inland and to the other coastal settlements along the north shore of the pontos. Your foresight will be long remembered and the benefits we now shall receive will all be due to your actions.

¬-------------------

{Rome_Near_Numantia_Text_01_Title}Warning from Lusotana
{Rome_Near_Numantia_Text_01_Text1}
Ave, Imperator!! --- The legion's scouts approach the city of Numantia, chief of the cities of Hispania Citerior. It is inhabited by the Arevaci, a resolute tribe of Celtiberian warriors known for their ferocity in battle. Not only is the city flanked by a steep hill and defensive river, but the tribe is allied to the more powerful Lusitani in the west, which declare that any attack on their allies will be a cause for war.

{Lusotana_Near_Numantia_Text_01_Title}Entering Arevaci Lands
{Lusotana_Near_Numantia_Text_01_Text1}
Warlord! You have now entered the land of our allies, the mighty Arevaci. They have long been our allies and a careful balance has lasted for generations. They are great warriors and are likely to mobilize a great army to stop us, so before you proceed, be aware of the consequences of attacking our friends.

{Lusotana_Attacks_Numantia_Text_01_Title}Attack upon the Arevaci
{Lusotana_Attacks_Numantia_Text_01_Text1}
Warlord! We are now attacking our former Arevaci allies, and it is only a matter of time before they mobilize the rest of their men from the countryside and Celtiberi allied tribes such as the Belli and the Titti. They will soon be ready to march on us! 

{Celtiberi_Aid_Lusotana_Text_01_Title}Arevaci Mobilization
{Celtiberi_Aid_Lusotana_Text_01_Text1}
Warlord, good news! The Arevaci mobilize! They hold true to our bonds of friendship and will ensure that any of our enemies will not invade our lands through the Celtiberi lands. 

{Arverni_Near_Numantia_Text_01_Title}Warning from Lusotana
{Arverni_Near_Numantia_Text_01_Text1}
Your forces are nearing the Celtiberian city of Numantia. The Lusitannan warn that they would consider an attack on their Celtiberian allies as grounds for war.

{Aedui_Near_Numantia_Text_01_Title}Warning from Lusotana
{Aedui_Near_Numantia_Text_01_Text1}
Your forces are nearing the Celtiberian city of Numantia. The Lusitannan warn that they would consider an attack on their Celtiberian allies as grounds for war.

{Qarthadast_Near_Numantia_Text_01_Title}Warning from Lusotana
{Qarthadast_Near_Numantia_Text_01_Text1}
Your forces are nearing the Celtiberian city of Numantia. The Lusitannan warn that they would consider an attack on their Celtiberian allies as grounds for war.

{Casse_Near_Numantia_Text_01_Title}Warning from Lusotana
{Casse_Near_Numantia_Text_01_Text1}
The Celtiberian peoples, and their city of Numantia, are near. While this may be an opportunity to conquer more land, we must be prepared to deal with the ramifications of fighting the Celtiberians. Aside from the strength of their own people, they are allies of a powerful nearby tribe, the Lusotannan, and seeking to fight with the Celtiberians will also lead to war with the Lusotannan.

¬-------------------

{Rome_Near_Messana_Text_01_Title}Warning: Roman forces near Messana
{Rome_Near_Messana_Text_01_Text1}
Senatores, the maneuver of our soldiers so close to the Straits of Messana and the isle of Sicily is a blatant violation of the treaties of 306 and 279, both of which pledge mutual recognition with the Poeni Carthaginians. Encroachment into the Punic sphere of influence will result in war, I fear...

¬-------------------

{Yuezhi_Invasion_Text_01_Title}The Yuezhi appear in east.
{Yuezhi_Invasion_Text_01_Text1}
A mighty people, the Yuezhi, have appeared northeast of Chighu. Heralded by the drumming of hooves beyond number, they have come in search of new grazing lands. Those who stand in the path of the Yuezhi must flee or submit, for what people can summon the strength to defeat such a host?

¬-------------------

{Yuezhi_Near_Chighu_Text_01_Title}Panic In Chighu!
{Yuezhi_Near_Chighu_Text_01_Text1}
The mighty Yuezhi horde camped nearby has caused panic in the settlement of Chighu. Blood-chilling tales of Yuezhi cruelty have created a mood desperation. Confusion, rioting, and looting have been widespread as many try flee the town, while others have been driven in from the countryside by the marauding Yuezhi. The governor's residence has been attacked by crowds and the garrison, unable to maintain order, has escorted the governor from the city to preserve his safety. Can we muster the armed strength to defeat this great host? If not, I fear the situation is hopeless.
¬-------------------

{Rhegion_Rebel_Reminder_Text_01_Title}Roman Traitors hold Rhegion
{Rhegion_Rebel_Reminder_Text_01_Text1}
Senatores, now that Tarentum has been taken, the legions are free to deal with the traitorous Roman army that holds the city of Rhegion. These men, charged by the Senate to protect the city from Pyrrhus, instead expelled and massacred the citizens. Rome was shamed in the eyes of its allies. Rhegion must be taken and the traitors punished so that the good name of Rome may be restored.

{Near_Rhegion_Rebel_Reminder_Text_01_Title}Roman Traitors hold Rhegion
{Near_Rhegion_Rebel_Reminder_Text_01_Text1}
Senatores, our forces are near Rhegion. The legions must soon deal with the traitorous Roman army that holds it. These men, charged by the Senate to protect the city from Pyrrhus, instead expelled and massacred the citizens. Rome was shamed in the eyes of its allies. Rhegion must be taken and the traitors punished so that the good name of Rome may be restored.

{Rhegion_Rebel_Captured_Text_01_Title}Rome's good name restored
{Rhegion_Rebel_Captured_Text_01_Text1}
Senatores, the legions have taken Rhegion from Roman traitors and restored the city to its inhabitants. Some 300 captured Roman renegades have been scourged and beheaded in the Forum. By this action the good name of Rome has been restored, so far as possible, among the allies.

¬-------------------

{Polybian_Reforms_Text_01_Title}A Reformed Army
{Polybian_Reforms_Text_01_Text1}
The wars of the last decades and our continuous battles with non Italian powers have to proven fruitful in some way. Our consuls have perfected manipular tactics and our milites have adopted some of the arms and armour of our enemies after their value was taught to us by the mercenaries of the poenii and warriors of the celtae.

¬-------------------

{Marian_Reforms_Text_01_Title}A Reformed Army
{Marian_Reforms_Text_01_Text1}
The enormous expansion of our Res Publica has caused some massive changes within our society. The number of small farmers and potential conscripts for the army is in steady decline since the great slave-based Latifundia began spreading over Italia. Every new year it becomes more difficult to recruit the necessary soldiers to defend our interests against the countless enemies of Roma. The number of men that fulfil the property requirements shrinks continuously. Even in the field our mighty legions had to suffer from some setbacks. But now one of our best generals has recognized the problems and initiated a series of reforms to solve them and increase the overall performance of the army.

¬-------------------

{Augustan_Reforms_Text_01_Title}A Reformed Army
{Augustan_Reforms_Text_01_Text1}
Things have changed dramatically and the republic is now only a part of our history. The countless civil wars have come to an end and the princeps is not longer only the first man of the senate, but rules the whole empire almost like a total monarch of the east. The size and organization of the army has adapted to the needs of the new era and is now a fully professional standing force of permanent units. The emperor is now its supreme commander and the military oath of the soldier bounds them only to him.
¬-------------------

{Aedui_Celt_Reform_1_Text_01_Title}Time of Bondsmen
{Aedui_Celt_Reform_1_Text_01_Text1}
Dramatic political and military events have transformed the Celtic world. This transformation has opened up new possibilities for the organization, composition, and equipment of Celtic armies. It is now time to begin laying the foundation of a new military.
¬-------------------

{Aedui_Celt_Reform_2_Text_01_Title}Time of Soldiers
{Aedui_Celt_Reform_2_Text_01_Text1}
A combination of external threats and internal strife has led to the necessity for Celts to develop larger standing armies. Warbands remain largely as augmentary bodies in Gaul, though still hold a status as the majority of British soldiers. However, in both cases, the warrior class has expanded greatly, with chiefs offering to pay for the equipment of soldiers, as opposed to soldiers needing to provide it themselves.
¬-------------------

{Saka_Reforms_Message_Text_01_Title}A New Army
{Saka_Reforms_Message_Text_01_Text1}
As we have expanded into distant regions, our warriors have learned much fighting foreign tribes, and we have made subjects of many strange peoples. We find these strangers often organize and equip their soldiers in an unusual, but perhaps not a useless, manner. The experience of our warriors and the recruitment of subject peoples can now transform the way we fight. It is now possible begin laying the foundation of a new army.
¬-------------------

{Comes_Of_Age_Agoge_Advisor_Text_01_Title}An important message!
{Comes_Of_Age_Agoge_Advisor_Text_01_Text1}
A young man in our family who has great potential can take part in the Spartan Agoge if he arrives in Sparte before he turns 20. There are some potential drawbacks, but especially if he shows promise already it may bring out the best in his character.
¬-------------------

{Character_Begins_Agoge_Text_01_Title}Agoge Training Begun
{Character_Begins_Agoge_Text_01_Text1}
One of our promising young officers has begun his training in the Spartan Agoge. He is currently in Sparte and should not leave the polis until this stage is complete, in approximately two years. Keep a close eye on his progress and allow him to complete his training there.
¬-------------------

{Character_Begins_Paidiskos_Text_01_Title}Paidiskos Training Begun
{Character_Begins_Paidiskos_Text_01_Text1}
Our promising young officer has completed his training in the Spartan Agoge and now must serve two additional years before he may join full army service. He must remain in or around Sparte, but not enter any other polis during this time. 
¬-------------------

{Character_Begins_Krypteia_Text_01_Title}Krypteia Training Begun
{Character_Begins_Krypteia_Text_01_Text1}
Our promising young officer has completed his training in the Spartan Agoge and is one of the very few who have been chosen to serve in the Krypteia for the next two years. This is a very special circumstance and he must be removed from the polis of Sparte itself immediately. For the next two years he must remain hidden in Lakonia, not in Sparte itself though. Do not join in any battles or associate with any other group of soldiers. Keep a close eye on him and keep him hidden, perhaps with a spy, but do not take him into any polis or take part in any battles during this time. 
¬-------------------

{Character_Completes_Agoge_Text_01_Title}Agoge Training Completed
{Character_Completes_Agoge_Text_01_Text1}
Finally our young officer has completed his training in the Spartan Agoge and his service for two years afterwards as well. He now has joined the standing army of adult citizen warriors and stands for election into a common mess here if he is a Spartan, and can return to his own people's army if he is not. Congratulations are due! 

¬-------------------

{Xanthippus_Text_01_Title}Great Sophet one of our Greek mercenaries wants to advise us.

{Xanthippus_Text_01_Text1}
Great Sophet, I bring interesting news from the army camp. As you know, our recruiters brought a considerable number of soldiers from Greece last winter. Among them there is a Xanthippos of Lacedaemon who says that we, the Qarthadastim, owe our defeats not to the Romans, but to ourselves, through the inexperience of our generals. We have summoned Xanthippos so that he can explain his estimate of the situation to the council of one hundred and four. He has said that we are making a grave mistake by avoiding the open ground because this restricts our elephants and our superior numbers in cavalry. He urges us to take his advice and you must decide quickly, great Sophet, if the generals should accept Xanthippos' advice and give him a special command, entrusting our forces to him, or if we should leave it to our own generals to solve the situation and send the arrogant Greek back to Sparta.

By pressing the portrait button you will accept Xanthippos. Press the "X" button (dismiss advice) if you want to reject him. 

¬-------------------

{Naravas_Text_01_Title}Our Massylian allies have sent us aid!

{Naravas_Text_01_Text1}
A force of Massylian Numidians has appeared on our borders! Though at first we believed them to be coming in aid of our foes it seems they are here to assist us. The young man leading them, a general of high rank named Naravas, has approached our encampments and bravely offered us his services out of the love for Kart-Hadast common in his house. His timing could not have been better for the hour is late and our situation dire. Hopefully these reinforcements will be enough to break the sieges of our enemies and drive them from our lands. 

¬-------------------

{Generic_Script_Text_01_Title}Generic Script Activation.

{Generic_Script_Text_01_Text1}
Click the "Show me how" button to run the script named in Generic_Script_Thread; see export_descr_advice.txt.\n

NOTE: If the "Show me how" button is grayed out, the script has an error. For debugging help, start EB with the show_err option. Please dismiss the Advisor with the "x" button; don't click the portrait button.

¬-------------------

{Shahanshah_Text_01_Title}Shahan Shah!
{Shahanshah_Text_01_Text1}
It is done! You have triumphed over your greatest enemies yet in the honor of Ahura Mazda, great Lord! The decadent Yonaw who took this land long ago have been crushed under the hooves of our proud horses and driven out of our rightful homeland. The land of the Aryans is once again in the hands of the Aryans. May Alaxsindar the Accursed turn in his grave and the fire of our Zarathushtrâi God burn brightly. You are now the Padixshah, who has no equal. Now is the time to make sure our reign in Iran. Make the other petty kings of this rich land your slaves, Shahan Shah, and claim your rightful destiny as successor to the kings of old! 

¬-------------------


