¬ Localisation file for transition screen quotes
¬ Lines in brackets are not to be translated

{Quote_3}
There is one thing, Gisgo, yet more astonishing, which you take no notice of. In all those great numbers before us, there is not one man called Gisgo
{Quote_4}
Ignoranti, quem portum petat, nullus suus ventus est - If a man does not know to what port he is sailing, no wind is favourable
{Quote_7}
Ah! The generals! They are numerous but not good for much!
{Quote_10}
We are the last people on earth, and the last to be free.
{Quote_11}
They make it a desert, and call it peace.
{Quote_16}
Lord, I praise you! You are my rock! You prepared my hands for war. You taught my fingers to fight.
{Quote_17}
Andraste basbhcoradhan - "Andrasta brings death to the wicked"
{Quote_18}
They say I am most beautiful of our tribe. How exquisite that I am then held to high standards. It is an honor to reward the gifts of the gods with dutiful service.
{Quote_19}
I care nothing for my own life. In the service of the tribe, the king, and the kingdom, are all that matter. I must defend it, and all who live within it.
{Quote_20}
Rome did not create a great empire by having meetings, they did it by killing all those who opposed them.
{Quote_21}
When the tyrant has disposed of foreign enemies by conquest or treaty, and there is nothing more to fear from them, then he is always stirring up some war or other, in order that the people may require a leader.
{Quote_22}
The purpose of all war is ultimately peace.
{Quote_23}
The outcome of the war is in our hands; the outcome of words is in the council.
{Quote_24}
Ten soldiers wisely led will beat a hundred without a head.
{Quote_25}
Ye gods, what dastards would our host command? Swept to the war, the lumber of the land.
{Quote_26}
And by a prudent flight and cunning save a life which valour could not, from the grave. A better buckler I can soon regain, But who can get another life again?
{Quote_27}
And he shall judge among the nations, and shall rebuke many people: and they shall beat their swords into plowshares, and their spears into pruninghooks: nation shall not lift up sword against nation, neither shall they learn war any more.
{Quote_29}
Let who will boast their courage in the field, I find but little safety from my shield, Nature's, not honour's law we must obey: This made me cast my useless shield away.
{Quote_30}
If a plague asks you for a coin, give it two and make it go away
{Quote_31}
Rabo!
{Quote_32}
If I shall love my Country, it should be beautiful. This one is, it will be my Home.
{Quote_33}
An army of sheep led by a lion would defeat an army of lions led by a sheep
{Quote_34}
It is pleasant, when the sea is high and the winds are dashing the waves about, to watch from the shores the struggles of another
{Quote_35}
Stop quoting law. We carry Swords
{Quote_36}
The man who runs away will fight again
{Quote_37}
There can be no covenants between men and lions, wolves and lambs can never be of one mind
{Quote_38}
It is the one with the least regrets over concessions to the enemy who will continue in the greatest security
{Quote_39}
Even for those who were worse in other ways it is right that first place be given to valor against enemies
{Quote_40}
In war there is no prize for runner-up
{Quote_41}
In war, when a commander becomes so bereft of reason and perspective that he fails to understand the dependence of arms on Divine guidance, he no longer deserves victory
{Quote_42}
Taking the first footstep with a good thought the second with a good word and the third with a good deed I entered Paradise
{Quote_43}
To me every bad Greek is a Barbarian and every good Barbarian is a Greek
{Quote_46}
The rulers of the States are the only ones who should have the privilege of lying
{Quote_49}
How often have cities allowed themselves to be persuaded into war, and that by advisers who were thought the wisest of men, and then been utterly destroyed by those whom they attacked!
{Quote_50}
And the Persians educate their children, beginning at five years old and going on till twenty, in three things only, in riding, in shooting, and in speaking the truth
{Quote_51}
Hannibal knew how to gain a victory, but not how to use it
{Quote_53}
A good general not only sees the way to victory, he also knows when victory is impossible
{Quote_54}
In war we must always leave room for strokes of fortune, and accidents that cannot be foreseen
{Quote_55}
Pardon one offence and you encourage the commission of many
{Quote_56}
We should provide in peace what we need in war
{Quote_57}
To everything there is a season; and a time for every purpose under heaven...A time of war and a time of peace
{Quote_58}
But to-day you are here, and your men behind you, stalwart and stout of limb, and to-morrow they shall have armour like our own. None could find fault with their thews and sinews, and as for their spirit, it is for us to see it does not fail.
{Quote_59}
He is best secure from dangers who is on his guard even when he seems safe
{Quote_61}
In war we must be speedy
{Quote_62}
A disorderly mob is no more an army than a heap of building materials is a house
{Quote_63}
Quick decisions are unsafe decisions
{Quote_64}
The cruelty of war makes for peace
{Quote_65}
Great empires are not maintained by timidity
{Quote_66}
Even the bravest are frightened by sudden terrors
{Quote_67}
Quisque est barbarus alio
{Quote_68}
A bad peace is even worse than war
{Quote_69}
The desire for safety stands against every great and noble enterprise
{Quote_70}
War is not so much a matter of weapons as of money
{Quote_71}
An ambush, if discovered and promptly surrounded, will repay the intended mischief with interest
{Quote_72}
Few men are born brave; many become so through training and force of discipline
{Quote_73}
A general is not easily overcome who can form a true judgement of his own and the enemy's forces
{Quote_74}
What can a soldier do who charges when out of breath?
{Quote_75}
Victory loves prudence
{Quote_76}
Tribunes with their tongues sentence men to death.
{Quote_77}
When one side goes against the enemy with the gods' gift of stronger morale, then their adversaries, as a rule, cannot withstand them
{Author_3}
Hannibal Barca, replying to a soldier astonished by the numerical superiority of the Romans at Cannae, 216BC
{Author_4}
Seneca
{Author_7}
Aristophanes
{Author_10}
Calgacus, leader of the Caledonians: Tacitus
{Author_11}
Calgacus, leader of the Caledonians: Tacitus
{Author_16}
The Bible: Psalm 144
{Author_17}
Inscription on a British idol to the goddess Andrasta
{Author_18}
Orriagh Raighnaigha
{Author_19}
Llwnn yn Orddae
{Author_20}
Unknown
{Author_21}
Plato
{Author_22}
Saint Augustine
{Author_23}
Homer
{Author_24}
Euripides
{Author_25}
Homer
{Author_26}
Archilochos
{Author_27}
The Bible, Isaiah 2:4
{Author_29}
Archilochos
{Author_30}
Punic Proverb
{Author_31}
Ancient Celtic or Iberian warcry; forerunner of the dark age and medieval Gaelic 'Abu'
{Author_32}
Teutonic Invaders in Italy
{Author_33}
Arab Proverb
{Author_34}
Lucretius
{Author_35}
Cn. Pompeius Magnus: Plutarch's Life of Pompey
{Author_36}
Menander
{Author_37}
Homer: Iliad, Achilles to Hector
{Author_38}
Thucydides: The Corcryaen speech to the Athenians
{Author_39}
Thucydides: Perikles' Funeral Oration
{Author_40}
Lucius Annaeus Seneca
{Author_41}
Lucius Annaeus Seneca
{Author_42}
Zoroaster
{Author_43}
Alexander the Great, as quoted by Eratosthenes of Cyrene
{Author_46}
Plato
{Author_49}
Kurush Wuzurg (Cyrus the Great)
{Author_50}
Herodotus
{Author_51}
Maharbal
{Author_53}
Polybius
{Author_54}
Polybius
{Author_55}
Publilius Syrus
{Author_56}
Publilius Syrus
{Author_57}
The Bible, Ecclesiastes 3:1-8
{Author_58}
Kurush Wuzurg (Cyrus the Great)
{Author_59}
Publilius Syrus
{Author_61}
Silius Italicus
{Author_62}
Socrates
{Author_63}
Sophacles
{Author_64}
Publius Statius
{Author_65}
Tacitus
{Author_66}
Tacitus
{Author_67}
Everyone is a barbarian to someone
{Author_68}
Tacitus
{Author_69}
Tacitus
{Author_70}
Thucydides
{Author_71}
Vegetius
{Author_72}
Vegetius
{Author_73}
Vegetius
{Author_74}
Vegetius
{Author_75}
Latin proverb
{Author_76}
Shakespeare: Titus Andronicus, III, 1
{Author_77}
Xenophon
{quote_78}
In the first place then thank the gods for this; for it is they who working to aid you to victory have led the enemy on to such ground, and next thank myself for compelling them to fight, a thing they can no longer avoid, and to fight here where the advantages are manifestly ours
{quoted_79}
Hannibal Barca, encouraging his troops before Cannae, 216BC (Polybius, Book 3)
{quote_80}
Tyn fian dwma fiatua!
{trans_81}
I am a freeman in a free state!
{quoted_82}
Last words of Dumnorix. Refused to be a hostage, and killed by Julius Caesar's men
{quote_83}
Timidios di Albhae Bren!
{trans_84}
For the true king of Britain!
{quoted_85}
Rallying cry of the Catuvellaunians/Casse
{quote_86}
Fight for your country - that is the best, the only omen!
{quoted_87}
Hector, addressing his army, in defiance of a sign from Zeus (Homer, the Iliad).
{quote_88}
...now in place of the young men urns and ashes are carried home to houses of the fighters
{quoted_89}
Aeschylus
{quote_90}
Beware lest in your anxiety to avoid war you obtain a master
{quoted_91}
Demosthenes
{quote_92}
War is sweet to those who have never experienced it
{quoted_93}
Pindar
{quote_94}
In war important events result from trivial causes
{quoted_95}
Gaius Julius Caesar
{quote_96}
Wĕshāfat bēn haggōyim, wĕhōkhī'akh lĕ'ammīm rabbīm; wĕkhittĕthū kharvōthām lĕ'ittīm, wakhănīthōthēhem lĕmazmērōth -- lō yissā goi el goi kherev, wĕlō yilmĕdū 'ōdh milkhāmā - And he shall judge among the nations, and shall rebuke many people; and they shall beat their swords into plowshares, and their spears into pruninghooks;
{trans_97}
nation shall not lift up sword against nation, neither shall they learn war any more.
{quoted_98}
Isaiah, 2:4
{quote_99}
ΠΑ ΒΩ ΚΑΙ ΤΑΝ ΓΑΝ ΚΙΝΗΣΩ
{trans_100}
Give me a place to stand, and I shall move the world
{quoted_101}
Archimedes
{quote_102}
Willing obedience always beats forced obedience
{quoted_103}
Xenophon
{quote_104}
The fortunes of war are always doubtful
{quoted_105}
Seneca
{quote_106}
The Spartans do not ask how many but where they are
{quoted_107}
Agis II of Sparta
{quote_108}
Come home with this shield or upon it
{quoted_109}
A Spartan woman equips her son
{quote_110}
Valour is superior to numbers
{quoted_111}
Vegetius
{quote_112}
Valour is the contempt of death and pain
{quoted_113}
Tacitus
{quote_114}
To lead untrained people to war is to throw them away
{quoted_115}
Confucius
{quote_116}
In war, truth is the first casualty
{quoted_117}
Aeschylus
{quote_118}
Dulce et decorum est pro patria mori
{trans_119}
It is a sweet and seemly thing to die for one's country
{quoted_120}
Horace
{quote_121}
Qui desiderat pacem praeparet bellum
{trans_122}
Let him who desires peace prepare for war
{quoted_123}
Vegetius
{quote_124}
An ambuscade, if discovered and promptly surrounded, will repay the intended mischief with interest
{quoted_125}
Vegetius
{quote_126}
The blade itself incites to violence
{quoted_127}
Homer
{quote_128}
Who was the first that forged the deadly blade? Of rugged steel his savage soul was made
{quoted_129}
Tibullus
{quote_130}
I swear so soon as age will permit I will use fire and steel to arrest the destiny of Rome
{quoted_131}
Hannibal Barca at the age of 9, ca. 238 BC
{quote_132}
Toutava, marae, da augu, tosgo, mavi Vergalla!
{trans_133}
For tribe, family, and honor, forward, sons of Great Gaul!
{quoted_134}
Inscription on a statue of Dis, the mythic founder of Gaul
{quote_135}
From the pride and arrogance of the Romans nothing is sacred. But the vengeful gods are now at hand. On this spot we must either conquer, or die with glory
{quoted_136}
Boudicca, as quoted by Tacitus, in Annals, XIV, 3
{quote_137}
The gods favour the bold
{quoted_138}
Ovid
{quote_139}
Great empires are not maintained by timidity
{quoted_140}
Tacitus
{quote_141}
Catuvellaunorix bathbanay acorrius cagoran
{trans_142}
King of the Catuvellauni, I am dead. I hope it was enough
{quoted_143}
Inscription on the tomb of an ancient British royal guard, presumably the guard's last words
{quote_144}
Only the brave enjoy noble and glorious deaths
{quoted_145}
Dionysius of Halicarnassus
{quote_146}
Few men are born brave; many become so through training and force of discipline
{quoted_147}
Vegetius
{quote_148}
Kōttū ittēkhem lakhărāvōth, ūmazmĕrōthēkhem lirmākhīm: hakhallāsh yōmar, 'gibbōr āni!'
{trans_149}
Beat your plowshares into swords, and your pruninghooks into spears: let the weak say, 'I am strong!'
{quoted_150}
Joel, 3:10
{quote_151}
In peace, sons bury their fathers; in war, fathers bury their sons
{quoted_152}
Herodotus
{quote_153}
How are the mighty fallen in the midst of battle!
{quoted_154}
II Samuel, I, 25
{quote_155}
The walls shall shake at the noise of the horsemen, and of the wheels, and of the chariots
{quoted_156}
Ezekiel, XXVI, 10
{quote_157}
Non mortem timemus, sed cogitationem mortis
{trans_158}
We do not fear death, but the thought of death
{quoted_159}
Seneca
{quote_160}
A collision at sea can ruin your entire day
{quoted_161}
Thucydides
{quote_162}
Quemadmoeum gladis nemeinum occidit, occidentis telum est
{trans_163}
A sword is never a killer, it's a tool in the killer's hands
{quoted_164}
Seneca
{quote_165}
Learn to obey before you command
{quoted_166}
Solon of Athens
{quote_167}
Behold the striking hammer of justice. Enemies of my people, know my name and woe
{quoted_168}
Inscription on figurines of Sucellos
{quote_169}
I have seen during my life many an old fool; but this one beats them all
{quoted_170}
Hannibal Barca, addressing Phormio's lecture on leadership
{quote_171}
Agomonos ta Caballos ta Terc assubio
{trans_172}
Agomonos and Caballos and Terc were here
{quoted_173}
Gallic inscription in Egypt
{quote_174}
Oderint dum metuant
{trans_175}
Let them hate provided that they fear
{quoted_176}
Unknown (Possibly Caligula)
{quote_177}
Courage may be taught as a child is taught to speak
{quoted_178}
Euripides
{quote_179}
Iniqua nunquam regna perpetuo manent
{trans_180}
Stern masters do not reign long
{quoted_181}
Seneca Philosophus
{quote_182}
Danger gleams like sunshine to a brave man's eyes
{quoted_183}
Euripides
{quote_184}
Constant exposure to dangers will breed contempt for them
{quoted_185}
Seneca
{quote_186}
A glorious death is his who for his country falls
{quoted_187}
Homer
{quote_188}
All warfare is based on deception
{quoted_189}
Sun Tzu
{quote_190}
Molon Labe - Come and get them
{quoted_191}
The reply of Leonidas to Xerxes' demand to surrender his arms before the battle at Thermopylae
¬{quote_192}
¬Alea iacta est
¬{trans_193}
¬Let the dice fly high!
¬{quoted_194}
¬Gaius Julius Caesar
{quote_195}
Nihil tam munitum quod non expugnari pecunia possit
{trans_196}
Nothing is so well fortified that money cannot capture it
{quoted_197}
Cicero
{quote_198}
The Romans were terrified by the fine order of the Celtic host, and the dreadful din, for there were innumerable hornblowers and trumpeters, and the whole army were shouting their war cries. Very terrifying too were the appearance and the gestures of the naked warriors in front, all in the prime of life and finely built men, and all in the leading companies richly adorned with gold torcs and armlets.
{quoted_199}
Polybius, The Histories, describing the Celts at Telamon
{quote_200}
I thought it necessary to speak at some length on this subject in order to show how foolish the Epirots were, and that no people, if wise, should ever admit a garrison stronger than their own forces, especially if composed of barbarians.
{quoted_201}
Polybius, The Histories, after writing about the betrayal of Epeiros by Gallic mercenaries
{quote_202}
If Rome wishes to rule the world, does it follow that all others wish to be slaves?
{quoted_203}
King Caratacus, as quoted by Tacitus
{quote_204}
Barbarians: Greek Historians ignore them, reserving their admiration for Greece only. We Romans too, have underestimated them, since in our devotion to antiquity we neglect modern history
{quoted_205}
Tacitus, Annals of Imperial Rome
{quote_206}
Self-control is the chief element in self-respect, and self-respect is the chief element in courage
{quoted_207}
Thucydides
{quote_208}
Cry "Havoc!" and let slip the dogs of war
{quoted_209}
Shakespeare: Julius Caesar, III, 1
{quote_210}
Right, as the world goes, is only in question between equals in power, while the strong do what they can, and the weak suffer what they must
{quoted_211}
Thucydides, quoting the Athenian envoy to the neutral Melians, explaining why they should submit without fighting
{quote_212}
The sinews of war are infinite money
{quoted_213}
Cicero
{quote_214}
He who knows when he can fight and when he cannot will be victorious
{quoted_215}
Sun Tzu
{quote_216}
The proper arts of a general are judgement and prudence
{quoted_217}
Tacitus
{quote_218}
Indeed they will be more than enough, even though the Romans are the greediest nation on earth!
{quoted_219}
Hannibal, asked by Antiochus if his richly ornamented army was enough to defeat the Romans at Magnesia, ca. 189BC
{quote_220}
Roman soldiers will march not whither the enemy summons them, but whither their commander leads them
{quoted_221}
Livy 8.23
{quote_222}
Generally management of the many is the same as management of the few. It is a matter of organization
{quoted_223}
Sun Tzu
{quote_224}
If a man does not strike first, he will be the first struck
{quoted_225}
Athenogoras of Syracuse
{quote_226}
The Greeks, a people valiant in words rather than in deeds
{quoted_227}
Livy 8.22
{quote_228}
In war, numbers alone confer no advantage. Do not advance relying on sheer military power
{quoted_229}
Sun Tzu
{quote_230}
This war had lasted for three years and four months, and it far excelled all wars we know of in cruelty and defiance of principle
{quoted_231}
Polybius, The Histories, On the Mercenaries War
{quote_232}
For whoever is not against us is for us
{quoted_233}
Jesus of Nazareth, Mark 9: 40
{quote_234}
Ō tempora!  Ō  mōrēs!
{trans_235}
O the times! O the morals!
{quoted_236}
Cicero - In Catilīnam
{quote_237}
Oculīs dēsignat ad mortem nōs!
{trans_238}
By means of his eyes he designates us to death!
{quoted_239}
Cicero - In Catilīnam
{quote_240}
Auribus teneō lupum
{trans_241}
I am holding the wolf by his ears
{quoted_242}
Terence
{quote_243}
It is narrated that as Xenophon was sacrificing to the gods, wearing a wreath, news came that his son had died. He was shaken, but continued, when he learned that he died fighting. He never shed a tear. 'I knew' he said 'that I raised a mortal'.
{quoted_244}
Diogenes Laertios ΙΙ,54-55, Vitae Philosophorum
{quote_245}
A city for sale, soon to fall if once it find a buyer.
{quoted_246}
Jugurtha looking back at Rome, The Jugurthine War, Ch. XXXV
{quote_247}
To my thinking, it is less dishonourable for a king to be surpassed in arms than in generosity.
{quoted_248}
King Bocchus I of Mauretania, The Jugurthine War, Ch. CX
{quote_249}
As Antisthenes was suffering from a serious and incurable disease, Diogenes of Sinope is mentioned to have given him a sword saying...'In case you would need the good services of a friend'
{quoted_250}
Julian, VI speech, 181 b.
{quote_251}
Antisthenes [wanting to display his frugal ways] was showing to everyone the holes in his clothes. "Through your clothes, I can see your vanity' [Socrates replied]
{quoted_252}
Diogenes Laertios II,36 and VI,8 Vitae Philosophorum
{quote_253}
Thales was proclaiming that death isn't any different than life. 'So, why don't you die?' someone asked. 'Because there is no difference' he replied.
{quoted_254}
Diogenes Laertios I,35, Vitae Philosophorum
{quote_255}
Your boldness and drunkenness, Antiochus, caused your fall; for you expected to drink up the Arsacid kingdom in huge cups.
{quoted_256}
Parthian king Arsaces VII (Phraates II) when he had buried Antiochus VII Sidetes - Poseidonios of Apamea, History, Bk. XVI
{quote_257}
De inimico non loquaris sed cogites
{trans_258}
Don't wish ill for your enemy, plan it.
{quoted_259}
Syrus
{quote_260}
Shall our family, then, never be at peace? Shall we always be harassed with war, bloodshed, and exile?
{quoted_261}
Adherbal, The Jugurthine War, Ch. XIV
{quote_262}
Have you remembered to enable the ===>EB SCRIPT<=== yet? If not, listen to your good advisor and click "Show me how" when he asks you to, or you won't get the real EB experience! The advisor may pop up at other times too, but unlike Vanilla RTW, in EB he always has something important to tell you. Ignore him at your peril ;). You may want to check the EB FAQ at http://forums.totalwar.org/vb/showthread.php?t=84854
{quoted_263}
EB team


¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************